<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<articles exportsource="mmbase://zilver.toly.net/null/foundation" timestamp="20100722140849">
	<node number="971" owner="admin">
		<body>The MMBase Foundation supports the community: users, commercial partners and developers. The developers have their own portal and organisation structure, their Management Committee advises the Foundation. The Foundation primarily looks after the interests of the users and commercial partners, but supports the developers where and if necessary. Major goal is to facilitate the web content management system for Open Source use with a focus on   stabilization, innovation and continuity of the software and community.</body>
		<lastmodified>-6</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>The goal of the MMBase Foundation is facilitating the content management system MMBase for Open Source usage, along with its community, focusing on the stabilization, innovation and continuity of the software.</intro>
		<offline>1735686054</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1060358514</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Foundation</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="973" owner="admin">
		<body>&lt;h3&gt;Roles &amp;amp; Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The MMBase community exists of roughly three groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the users, sponsors, and developers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of this document focuses on developers, whose  exact roles and responsibilities are based on merit. Everybody can help no matter what their role, but those who have been long term or valuable contributors to the project may obtain rights to vote on source changes and commit directly to the source repository. These subgroups (the Committers and the MMC	members) are detailed below along with the more broader community groups.

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;Users&lt;/h3&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Users are the people who use the products of the Project. People in this role aren't contributing code, but they are using the products, reporting bugs, making feature requests, and such. When a user starts to contribute code or documentation patches, they become a developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users may include administrators, end-users (editors), web-designers, and other interested parties. Users can post their questions and finsings on the MMBase user mailinglist (&lt;A HREF=&quot;mailto:users@mmbase.org&quot;&gt;users@mmbase.org&lt;/A&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;Sponsors&lt;/h3&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Sponsors are those organisations that support the MMBase community through contributions other than development, such as providing hardware, promotion through marketing, or by making monetary donations.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sponsors can operate on their own, or through the MMBase Foundation, which supports the MMBase community by taking care of facilities needed for the continuing development of MMBase. Such facilities include maintaining the website, organizing events and courses, marketing, and writing documentation.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foundation does not have influence on the development of MMBase, but can provide input, report bugs, and communicate desires as any other MMBase user, and may provide advise on the development of components by third parties.

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;Developers&lt;/h3&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Developers are the people who write code or documentation patches or contribute positively to MMBase in other ways. A developer's contribution is always recognized. In source code, all developers who contribute to a source file may have their name added to the list of authors for that file (in the java documentation of the +&gt;developers@mmbase.org&lt;/A&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers may go inactive for a variety of reasons. A Developer that has been inactive for 6 months or more may lose his or her status as a Developer (be removed from the site). The MMC needs to confirm the inactivity fo the developer, but need not call a vote (this is mostly an administrative task).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers may also lose there status due to bad behavior such as harassament or flaming. Developers who lose their status this way are removed from the site and banned from the developers' mailinglist. Due to the latter measure, a unanimous, non-negative call need succeed (see voting, below).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;CVS rules&lt;/h4&gt;



&lt;p&gt;A developer has no submitting rights in the MMBase CVS repository. If a developer wants to get something into CVS, he or she has to ask a committer to submit the changes. The committer is responsible for the new code, and for adding the developer's name to the java documentation.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Coding rules&lt;/h4&gt;



&lt;p&gt;All Java language source code in the repository must be written in conformance to the code conventions that have been set of the MMBase project. These code conventions are an extension of the &amp;quot;Code Conventions for the Java Programming Language&amp;quot; as published by Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun rules can be found at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/&quot;&gt;http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more specific MMBase conventions are available from the MMBase website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The committor that accepts the code is responsible for checking whether the coding rules are followed.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;Committers&lt;/h3&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Developers who give frequent and valuable contributions to MMBase projects can have their status promoted to that of a &amp;quot;Committer&amp;quot; for that subproject. A Committer has write access to the source code repository and gains voting rights allowing them to affect the future of the subproject. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note&lt;/em&gt;: except where noted below, all rules for a Developer also apply to a Committor.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Becoming a committer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for a Developer to become a Committer, another Committer can nominate that Developer or the Developer can ask for it. Once a Developer is nominated, the commiters vote for allowing the committer access. This is a unanimous non-negative call (see voting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the calls succeeds, the Developer is converted into a Committer and given write access to the source code repository.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Loosing committer status&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Committers may go inactive for a variety of reasons. A Committer that has been inactive for 3 months or more may lose his or her status as a Committer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activity as a committer is measured in participation in projects and voting, and in the submission of bugfixes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Committers may also lose there status if they break the committer rules. A committor receives a warning from the MMC when he breaks a rule (i.e. a CVS rule, a Hack or Project rule, or casting a VETO without motivation). After three warnings, the MMC may take up contact with the committer to ask him to resign. If the committer is not willing, a unanimous, non-negative call need succeed,  on the developer list (see voting, below), in which the committer cannot participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MMC is entitled to temporarily disallow CVS access to that committor for the duration of the call.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;CVS rules:&lt;/h4&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Three types of changes can be committed to the source code repository (CVS):

&lt;ul&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;Changes in or additions to the	code related to an approved MMBase project, of which the committer is a member (generally no voting needed, see voting and projects)&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;Confirmed bug fixes (no voting needed)&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;Code that was written outside of an approved project and is not a bug-fix (a hack), and that has been approved by the community through a majority call with a 3-vote margin (see voting).&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;MMBase Management Committee (MMC)&lt;/h3&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;Committers who frequently participate with valuable contributions and know sufficient about the core of MMBase may have their status promoted to that of a &amp;quot;MMBase Management Committee Member&amp;quot;. This committee is the official managing body of the MMBase project and is responsible for setting overall project direction. In order to become a Member, someone  	the MMC must nominate the Committer. The individual may then be approved though a unanimous non-negative vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note&lt;/em&gt;: except where noted below, all rules for a Committor also apply to a MMC member.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;CVS rules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A MMC member has the same rights to CVS as other Committors. A MMC member also has a responsibility for the consistency of the CVS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MMC members are entitled to rollback changes if committed code puts the CVS in a  broken state, or whenever the CVS rules were not followed (i.e. a Hack that did not receive a majority vote was committed).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Other Responsibilities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MMC is responsible for the release of a stable MMBase distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any developer or user can participate in creating the release, but at least one MMC members should monitor the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers may create their own distributions, but the MMC carries no responsibilities for these releases.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;Project Rules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A MMBase project is an project that is approved by the MMC. When the project is finished it will be part of MMBase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An MMBase project meets the following criteria:

&lt;ul&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;The goal of the project is to add or improve MMBase functionality&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;A project leader is responsible for managing the project, committing the new code and/or delivering documentation. (This doesn't mean the project leader has to commit or write documentation himself! This can be delegated to a team member.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;The project has been approved by the MMC. This is done by proposing the project to the MMC. All developers propose  and participate in a project, but only a committer can be a project leader. The MMC votes to approve the project (this is a majority vote with a 3-vote margin), and detemrines the project leader. It is possible for a developer to be given committors status for the duration of a project, so that he can act as the project leader, or to allow him cvs access. In this case, a voting call is made as normal, but the committor status is revoked at the end of the project lifecycle (the duration need be stated explicitly when the call is made).&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;The project has to be documented on the MMBase site. The project leader is responsible for keeping the documentation up-to-date. (For instance the project leader adjusts the status of the project.)&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;The MMC may decide when to give the project CVS access. A project that has no CVS accass (yet) may not submit code - only write documentation and make proposals. A project with limited CVS access may only majke changes with approvement of the MMC. A project wiyth full CVS access may add or change code as required for the project.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Project leader &amp;amp; members&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project consists of one project leader and any number of project members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project leader need to be a committer. Developers van join a project as members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project leader starts the project after the MMC has opened it, and is the only one who can make decisions. Project members can propose a decision to the project leader who can grant the decision adding the decision to their project at MMBase.org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don't agree with a made decision contact the project member who proposed the decision and try to find out who is right. If the decision has to change contact the project leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a conflict ensues, the decision may be decided by the project leader or a vote need be called. Votes due to conflicts in decisions need be documented on the project  page at the MMBase site, as part of the decision.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Project documentation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project leader has to inform the MMBase community about the project. This is done by keeping the project information at MMBase.org up to date. When a person starts a project he has to inform the MMBase community by writing an article that can be added to the site and can be posted to the mailing lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project documentation on the site includes:

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The name of the project leader and team members,&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The status, start date and date of the latest change,&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The deliverables (including the code and documentation),&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;A short description of the project (including the goal).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;If applicable, a longer description detailing the project's approach and theories, any steps or phases in the project, it's progress, and any changes made to	goal or approach during development.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Code documentation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When starting a project, the project	leader describes the goal of the project, and the way this will be achieved. This includes a detailed description of the functionality that the new code adds to MMBase. This is the start of the documentation of the code. At the end of the project, the documentation is finished and includes the following:

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The author, project leader and project members&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The date the documentation is finished&lt;li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;A list of all the code that is related to the project (including new code, changed code, related existing MMBase code and other software that interacts with the new code)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;A description of the new functionality&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;A description of how the new code works&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;An example of the functionality, preferably including a working example&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;An installation guide&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;A description of how the new code interacts with other MMBase code and other software&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Full api documentation.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the documentation is to enable all MMBase users (with the right skills) to use the new functionality.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;Hack Rules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Hack is new MMBase functionality that someone wants to be added to the MMBase source in the CVS. Before the Hack will be added it has to follow the follow the following criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A MMBase Hack meets the following criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The goal of the Hack is to add or improve MMBase functionality&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The Hack has to be approved by MMBase MMC and Committers. This is done by proposing the Hack to the MMBase developer list and calling for a majority vote. Hacks can be proposed by developers, but only committers can vote.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The Hack has to be documented on the MMBase site.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The MMC may decide that an approved Hack is too involved, and may decide to make it a project instead, which means the hack needs to follow the project rules.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;A Hack needs to contain the following documentation:

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The names of the persons who helped by making the hack.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The status, start date and date of the latest change.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;A short design of how the code works.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;A description of the new functionality of the new hack.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;An installation guide (if needed).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;At least one working example.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;A list of all the code that is related to the project (including new code, changed code, related existing MMBase code and other software that interacts with the new code)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;And least but not last, all have to contain apidoc information.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the documentation is to enable all MMBase users (with the right skills) to use the new functionality.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;Bugfix Rules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bugfix is a piece of code that fixes an error or misbehavior that occurs in the existing code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a bugfix changes the functionality of the code (other than solving errors), it is  not a bugfix but a Hack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not necessery to vote for a bugfix,but fixes need to be tested and confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All fixes need be documented when submitted in the MMBase CVS (in the CVS log). The documentation requires explanantion of the  fix, the committers name, and reference	to the MMBase bugtracker if applicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All errors need be documented in the MMBase bugtracker (even as they are solved). This allows users to trace bugs in older products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; adding javadocs, while not technically a bug fix, follows the rules of bugfixing (except you don't add them in the bugtracker).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;Voting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When decisions have to be made about MMBase, be it code changes, assigning projects or responsibilities, or on membership as a Committor or on the MMC, a process of voting takes place.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;MMC&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting takes place within the MMC when it deals with opening a project, assigning or revoking CVS access to a project, the includion of expellation fo an MMC member, or when making choices regarding tasks performed by the MMC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most calls for voting within the MMC are majority calls with a margin of 3 votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Exceptions:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case of admittance of a new member, this must be an unanimous non-negative call, with a margin of 3 votes. The candidate member is not allowed to vote.(This rule may be dropped in favor of election through the MMbase Community)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case of expulsion of a member, this must be an unanimous positive call. The member concerned is not allowed to vote. (This rule may be dropped in favor of election through the MMbase Community)

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All MMC calls are held during the MMC meetings or during the MMChat, or on the MMC mailinglist. Calls during meetings are resolved immediately. Calls on the list are resolved in the same manner as community calls (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; A MMC vote and its decision needs to be made public after voting, even if the vote failed.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting takes place within a project when it deals with closing a project (either finishing it or putting it on hold), or with code changes that fall within the scope of that project and that do not affect other projects or the MMBase core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

	Changes that affects other projects

	need the permission (by default, a majority vote) from the other

	project. Changes that affects non-project code need to be voted on by

	the community (the committers).

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project leader asks the other project's permission, or  calls the vote on the developers list as if it was a vote for committers (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, votes within a project are majority votes with no margin, conducted during meetings, though the project leader may agree on a different voting system, or call a decision in case of conflict (see project leaders and decisions, 	above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, project calls should NOT be run on the developer mailinglist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of a vote (succesful or not) may be published on the MMBase website project page (as a decision, or as a change in the project status), as decided by the project leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: if a project has been granted CVS access by the MMC, and code changes or additions fall within the scope of the project and do not affect other code, no calls need be made to the community. The projectleader is responsible for any changes made.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Community&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting takes place amongst committers, on the developerlist, when it deals with changes in the code that are not bugfixes or part of a project. Project leaders and MMC members may call for votes to be cast regarding issues that deal outside their jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calls for voting within the community are majority calls with a margin of 3 votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All calls are held on the MMBase developers mailinglist. Only committors are allowed to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note&lt;/em&gt;: a committor need not call a vote for submitting a bugfix, but a bugfix should be registered in the MMBase bugtracker so people can find sources of problems in older versions of MMBase.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Voting Process&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calls in the community are held on the developer malinglist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These calls (as well as calls made on the MMC list) are resolved as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person who calls the vote sends an email to the list, indicating that it is a call for a vote by including &lt;CODE&gt;CALL:&amp;lt;subject&amp;gt;&lt;/CODE&gt; in the subject header, with &lt;CODE&gt;&amp;lt;subject&amp;gt;&lt;/CODE&gt; being a short description of the call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The body of the message should contain the following set up:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;CALL FOR:&lt;br /&gt;

&amp;lt;description of the call(required) &amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;

LINKS:&lt;br /&gt;

&amp;lt;any link to sources, examples, documentation&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;

START OF CALL: &amp;lt;date voting starts&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;

END OF CALL: &amp;lt;date voting ends&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;

[_] +1 (YEA)&lt;br /&gt;

[_] +0 (ABSTAIN )&lt;br /&gt;

[_] -1 (NAY), because :&lt;br /&gt;

[_] VETO, because:&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Committors have till the given end-of-call date to react. The person who makes the call cannot vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end-of-vote date is by default three working days after the start-of-vote day (so a  call on friday ends five days later, on wednesday). The duration of the call may be extended (but not shortened) by the person who made the call, or by a member of the MMC, to enable a sufficient number of committors to respond.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;When reacting on a call, committors send a reply, quoting only the line that indicates their vote. The following votes can be made :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible votes:

&lt;ul&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;YEA&lt;/b&gt; (+1) : This counts as one positive vote. Any call needs at least one positive vote. Vote YEA if you believe the change will improve MMBase.&lt;/li&gt;



  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;ABSTAIN&lt;/b&gt; (+0) : This vote does not count towards the total. It does not cancel a positive vote but may affect outcome if the margin is not made. Vote ABSTAIN if you cannot decide whether the change is an improvement.&lt;/li&gt;



  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;NAY&lt;/b&gt; (-1): This counts as one negative vote.A negative vote cancels one positive vote, and may affect the outcome if the margin is not made. Vote NAY only if you believe the change will not improve MMBase, but if you are willing to resign to a majority vote. You need to explain why you vote NAY, and whether any change in the proposal will affect your vote. If you do not explain, your vote becomes an ABSTAIN.&lt;/li&gt;



  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;VETO&lt;/b&gt; : this is a veto, and means you will not accept the change. You need to explain why you VETO, and whether any change in the proposal will affect that vote. If you do not explain, your vote becomes an ABSTAIN. If the explanation is sound and there is no posibility of changing the proposal, the call fails, regardless of the number of positive votes.

  &lt;p&gt;A VETO means you find the call unacceptable, to a degree that you end the call regardless of other people's opinions. A VETO states that other people have no need to vote any more. The call is over. The problem you found is simply too serious.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As such, when you are not sure, you should not VETO. If you think that your vote might become a VETO (but you're not sure yet), give a negative vote with a warning that it &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; become a VETO, OR petition the MMC or the person making the call to hold the call until you have made up your mind. Casting a VETO which you later withdraw means you give other people no chance to vote&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Casting a VETO without sufficient motivation is a violation of the committor rules, and will be cause for a warning. A committor who abuses his rights and gets three warnings may loose his committor status (see Loosing Committor Status).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A VETO should not be used if the intention of a call is unclear, for that, petition for a hold (see below). If the person making the call repeatedly refuses to explain or document his change, or refuses to provide sources, if needed, and if a request to hold the call is not honored, you may resort to a VETO, but only as a last resort. Whimsically using a VETO to stop a call because you do not at first understand the ramifications is, as written above, a violation of the rules.&lt;/p&gt;



  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;PETITION&lt;/b&gt;: If there is a lack of explanation or resources, or if you need a period of debate to help you determine your vote, you can petition either the personn making the call or the MMC to hold the call until full explanation is given. Holding a call means it will not be resolved until it has been satisfactory discussed. This gives you the chance to make a informed choice without the three day limit time pressure. You can still vote when a call is put on hold.

    &lt;p&gt;Petitioning is not included as an option in the default Call form, but you can petition at any time you feel inadequately informed.&lt;/p&gt; 

  &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The eventual result of a call is determined by the type of call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most votes are majority calls, but the MMC may use more restrictive calls for important issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The counting of the votes is performed by one of the MMC members (designated by the MMC).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;Types of Calls&lt;/h4&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Majority call&lt;/b&gt; : A majority call is determined by tallying the positive votes and subtracting the negative votes and comparing the result with the margin of the call.

    &lt;p&gt;Unless specified otherwise, majority calls have a margin of three votes. This means that for the vote to succeed, the positive votes need to outrank the negative votes by three votes.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If this margin is not made, or if someone casts a VETO, the vote fails. If the vote fails because the margin was not made and not everyone had voted in time, the call may be extended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;



  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Unanimous non-negative call&lt;/b&gt;: All votes need be positive (YEA) or abstained.

    &lt;p&gt;The call always has a margin of 3 positive votes.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The call fails is someone casts a negative vote or a veto, or if the margin is not made.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;



  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Unanimous positive call&lt;/b&gt;: All votes need be positive (YEA).

    &lt;p&gt;The call fails if someone abstains, or casts a negative vote or a veto.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This call requires that everyone votes, and is only used by the MMC when expulsion of a member is called for.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1064150685</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1064150685</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1064150685</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase guidelines</title>
		<created>1064150685</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="975" owner="admin">
		<body>&lt;P&gt;The MMBase developers are the core part of the MMBase project. Without these developers, in fact, there would be no MMBase project. The roles and responsibilities that people assume within the project are based on merit. Everyone can help regardless of what their role is. The developers community is very active. Every day information exchange takes place on the mailing list and the IRC (MMBase chat). The MMBase management Committee and the Committers do their best to manage all processes. &lt;/P&gt;

&lt;P&gt;MMBase Management Committee. &lt;BR&gt;The MMBase Management Committee consists of 5&amp;nbsp;developers who have made major contributions to the project and have in depth knowledge of the system. The MMC coordinates the Open Source process,&amp;nbsp;the MMBase projects, the&amp;nbsp;code that is&amp;nbsp;added to the core. They make release plans and manage CVS. &lt;/P&gt;

&lt;P&gt;Committers&lt;BR&gt;The MMC&amp;nbsp;is supported by a group of eleven committers who can also make immediate changes in the core of MMBase. A vote is taken on every important change in the core. The Committers are developers who have frequently added valuable code to MMBase. Committers are people who know very well how MMBase is constructed, and they also know what they can and may add to the CVS.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Developers&lt;BR&gt;The Developers are all those people who are involved in the MMBase process. Developers inform us about bugs and try to solve these bugs. All people seriously working on MMBase can obtain the status of developer. If a Developer frequently submits code that is valuable to MMBase, the status of the Developer could&amp;nbsp;be upgraded to Committer.&lt;/P&gt;

&lt;P&gt;Foundation. The foundation is founded to facilitate the developers community, and organisations that are using MMBase. The MMC communicates with the foundation to keep each other informed. For more information about the foundation we refer to the foundation portal.&lt;/P&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1064151186</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1064151186</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1064151186</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase developers community</title>
		<created>1064151180</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="977" owner="admin">
		<body>1. Definitions. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.1. ``Contributor'' means each entity that creates or contributes to the creation of Modifications. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.2. ``Contributor Version'' means the combination of the Original Code, prior modifications used by a Contributor, and the Modifications made by that particular Contributor. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.3. ``Covered Code'' means the Original Code or Modifications or the combination of the Original Code and Modifications, in each case including portions thereof. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.4. ``Electronic Distribution Mechanism'' means a mechanism generally accepted in the software development community for the electronic transfer of data. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.5. ``Executable'' means Covered Code in any form other than Source Code. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.6. ``Initial Developer'' means the individual or entity identified as the Initial Developer in the Source Code notice required by Exhibit A. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.7. ``Larger Work'' means a work which combines Covered Code or portions thereof with code not governed by the terms of this License. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.8. ``License'' means this document. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.9. ``Modifications'' means any addition to or deletion from the substance or structure of either the Original Code or any previous Modifications. When Covered Code is released as a series of files, a Modification is: &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;A. Any addition to or deletion from the contents of a file containing Original Code or previous Modifications. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;B. Any new file that contains any part of the Original Code or previous Modifications. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.10. ``Original Code'' means Source Code of computer software code which is described in the Source Code notice required by Exhibit A as Original Code, and which, at the time of its release under this License is not already Covered Code governed by this License. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.11. ``Source Code'' means the preferred form of the Covered Code for making modifications to it, including all modules it contains, plus any associated interface definition files, scripts used to control compilation and installation of an Executable, or a list of source code differential comparisons against either the Original Code or another well known, available Covered Code of the Contributor's choice. The Source Code can be in a compressed or archival form, provided the appropriate decompression or de-archiving software is widely available for no charge. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;1.12. ``You'' means an individual or a legal entity exercising rights under, and complying with all of the terms of, this License or a future version of this License issued under Section 6.1. For legal entities, ``You'' includes any entity which controls, is controlled by, or is under common control with You. For purposes of this definition, ``control'' means (a) the power, direct or indirect, to cause the direction or management of such entity, whether by contract or otherwise, or (b) ownership of fifty percent (50%) or more of the outstanding shares or beneficial ownership of such entity. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;2. Source Code License. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;2.1. The Initial Developer Grant. &lt;br /&gt;The Initial Developer hereby grants You a world-wide, royalty-free, non-exclusive license, subject to third party intellectual property claims: &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;(a) to use, reproduce, modify, display, perform, sublicense and distribute the Original Code (or portions thereof) with or without Modifications, or as part of a Larger Work; and &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;(b) under patents now or hereafter owned or controlled by Initial Developer, to make, have made, use and sell (``Utilize'') the Original Code (or portions thereof), but solely to the extent that any such patent is reasonably necessary to enable You to Utilize the Original Code (or portions thereof) and not to any greater extent that may be necessary to Utilize further Modifications or combinations. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;2.2. Contributor Grant. &lt;br /&gt;Each Contributor hereby grants You a world-wide, royalty-free, non-exclusive license, subject to third party intellectual property claims: &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;(a) to use, reproduce, modify, display, perform, sublicense and distribute the Modifications created by such Contributor (or portions thereof) either on an unmodified basis, with other Modifications, as Covered Code or as part of a Larger Work; and &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;(b) under patents now or hereafter owned or controlled by Contributor, to Utilize the Contributor Version (or portions thereof), but solely to the extent that any such patent is reasonably necessary to enable You to Utilize the Contributor Version (or portions thereof), and not to any greater extent that may be necessary to Utilize further Modifications or combinations. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;3. Distribution Obligations. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;3.1. Application of License. &lt;br /&gt;The Modifications which You create or to which You contribute are governed by the terms of this License, including without limitation Section 2.2. The Source Code version of Covered Code may be distributed only under the terms of this License or a future version of this License released under Section 6.1, and You must include a copy of this License with every copy of the Source Code You distribute. You may not offer or impose any terms on any Source Code version that alters or restricts the applicable version of this License or the recipients' rights hereunder. However, You may include an additional document offering the additional rights described in Section 3.5. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;3.2. Availability of Source Code. &lt;br /&gt;Any Modification which You create or to which You contribute must be made available in Source Code form under the terms of this License either on the same media as an Executable version or via an accepted Electronic Distribution Mechanism to anyone to whom you made an Executable version available; and if made available via Electronic Distribution Mechanism, must remain available for at least twelve (12) months after the date it initially became available, or at least six (6) months after a subsequent version of that particular Modification has been made available to such recipients. You are responsible for ensuring that the Source Code version remains available even if the Electronic Distribution Mechanism is maintained by a third party. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;3.3. Description of Modifications. &lt;br /&gt;You must cause all Covered Code to which you contribute to contain a file documenting the changes You made to create that Covered Code and the date of any change. You must include a prominent statement that the Modification is derived, directly or indirectly, from Original Code provided by the Initial Developer and including the name of the Initial Developer in (a) the Source Code, and (b) in any notice in an Executable version or related documentation in which You describe the origin or ownership of the Covered Code. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;3.4. Intellectual Property Matters &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;(a) Third Party Claims. &lt;br /&gt;If You have knowledge that a party claims an intellectual property right in particular functionality or code (or its utilization under this License), you must include a text file with the source code distribution titled ``LEGAL'' which describes the claim and the party making the claim in sufficient detail that a recipient will know whom to contact. If you obtain such knowledge after You make Your Modification available as described in Section 3.2, You shall promptly modify the LEGAL file in all copies You make available thereafter and shall take other steps (such as notifying appropriate        mailing lists or newsgroups) reasonably calculated to inform those who received the Covered Code that new knowledge has been obtained. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;(b) Contributor APIs. &lt;br /&gt;If Your Modification is an application programming interface and You own or control patents which are reasonably necessary to implement that API, you must also include this information in the LEGAL file. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;3.5. Required Notices. &lt;br /&gt;You must duplicate the notice in Exhibit A in each file of the Source Code, and this License in any documentation for the Source Code, where You describe recipients' rights relating to Covered Code. If You created one or more Modification(s), You may add your name as a Contributor to the notice described in Exhibit A. If it is not possible to put such notice in a particular Source Code file due to its structure, then you must include such notice in a location (such as a relevant directory file) where a user would be likely to look for such a notice. You may choose to offer, and to charge a fee for, warranty, support, indemnity or liability obligations to one or more recipients of Covered Code. However, You may do so only on Your own behalf, and not on behalf of the Initial Developer or any Contributor. You must make it absolutely clear than any such warranty, support, indemnity or liability obligation is offered by You alone, and You hereby agree to indemnify the Initial Developer and every Contributor for any liability incurred by the Initial Developer or such Contributor as a result of warranty, support, indemnity or liability terms You offer. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;3.6. Distribution of Executable Versions. &lt;br /&gt;You may distribute Covered Code in Executable form only if the requirements of Section 3.1-3.5 have been met for that Covered Code, and if You include a notice stating that the Source Code version of the Covered Code is available under the terms of this License, including a description of how and where You have fulfilled the obligations of Section 3.2. The notice must be conspicuously included in any notice in an Executable version, related documentation or collateral in which You describe recipients' rights relating to the Covered Code. You may distribute the Executable version of Covered Code under a license of Your choice, which may contain terms different from this License, provided that You are in compliance with the terms of this License and that the license for the Executable version does not attempt to limit or alter the recipient's rights in the Source Code version from the rights set forth in this License. If You distribute the Executable version under a different license You must make it absolutely clear that any terms which differ from this License are offered by You alone, not by the Initial Developer or any Contributor. You hereby agree to indemnify the Initial Developer and every Contributor for any liability incurred by the Initial Developer or such Contributor as a result of any such terms You offer. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;3.7. Larger Works. &lt;br /&gt;You may create a Larger Work by combining Covered Code with other code not governed by the terms of this License and distribute the Larger Work as a single product. In such a case, You must make sure the requirements of this License are fulfilled for the Covered Code. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;4. Inability to Comply Due to Statute or Regulation. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;If it is impossible for You to comply with any of the terms of this License with respect to some or all of the Covered Code due to statute or regulation then You must: (a) comply with the terms of this License to the maximum extent possible; and (b) describe the limitations and the code they affect. Such description must be included in the LEGAL file described in Section 3.4 and must be included with all distributions of the Source Code. Except to the extent prohibited by statute or regulation, such description must be sufficiently detailed for a recipient of ordinary skill to be able to understand it. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;5. Application of this License. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;This License applies to code to which the Initial Developer has attached the notice in Exhibit A, and to related Covered Code. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;6. Versions of the License. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;6.1. New Versions. &lt;br /&gt;Netscape Communications Corporation (``Netscape'') may publish revised and/or new versions of the License from time to time. Each version will be given a distinguishing version number. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;6.2. Effect of New Versions. &lt;br /&gt;Once Covered Code has been published under a particular version of the License, You may always continue to use it under the terms of that version. You may also choose to use such Covered Code under the terms of any subsequent version of the License published by Netscape. No one other than Netscape has the right to modify the terms applicable to Covered Code created under this License. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;6.3. Derivative Works. &lt;br /&gt;If you create or use a modified version of this License (which you may only do in order to apply it to code which is not already Covered Code governed by this License), you must (a) rename Your license so that the phrases ``Mozilla'', ``MOZILLAPL'', ``MOZPL'', ``Netscape'', ``NPL'' or any confusingly similar phrase do not appear anywhere in your license and (b) otherwise make it clear that your version of the license contains terms which differ from the Mozilla Public License and Netscape Public License. (Filling in the name of the Initial Developer, Original Code or Contributor in the notice described in Exhibit A shall not of themselves be deemed to be modifications of this License.) &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;7. DISCLAIMER OF WARRANTY. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;COVERED CODE IS PROVIDED UNDER THIS LICENSE ON AN ``AS IS'' BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, WARRANTIES THAT THE COVERED CODE IS FREE OF DEFECTS, MERCHANTABLE, FIT FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR NON-INFRINGING. THE ENTIRE RISK AS TO THE QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE OF THE COVERED CODE IS WITH YOU. SHOULD ANY COVERED CODE PROVE DEFECTIVE IN ANY RESPECT, YOU (NOT THE INITIAL DEVELOPER OR ANY OTHER CONTRIBUTOR) ASSUME THE COST OF ANY NECESSARY SERVICING,  REPAIR OR CORRECTION. THIS DISCLAIMER OF WARRANTY CONSTITUTES AN ESSENTIAL PART OF THIS LICENSE. NO USE OF ANY COVERED CODE IS AUTHORIZED HEREUNDER EXCEPT UNDER THIS DISCLAIMER. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;8. TERMINATION. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;This License and the rights granted hereunder will terminate automatically if You fail to comply with terms herein and fail to cure such breach within 30 days of becoming aware of the breach. All sublicenses to the Covered Code which are properly granted shall survive any termination of this License. Provisions which, by their nature, must remain in effect beyond the termination of this License shall survive. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;9. LIMITATION OF LIABILITY. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES AND UNDER NO LEGAL THEORY, WHETHER TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE), CONTRACT, OR OTHERWISE, SHALL THE INITIAL DEVELOPER, ANY OTHER CONTRIBUTOR, OR ANY DISTRIBUTOR OF COVERED CODE, OR ANY SUPPLIER OF ANY OF SUCH PARTIES, BE LIABLE TO YOU OR ANY OTHER PERSON FOR ANY INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OF ANY CHARACTER INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, DAMAGES FOR LOSS OF GOODWILL, WORK STOPPAGE, COMPUTER FAILURE OR MALFUNCTION, OR ANY AND ALL OTHER COMMERCIAL  DAMAGES OR LOSSES, EVEN IF SUCH PARTY SHALL HAVE BEEN INFORMED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES. THIS LIMITATION OF LIABILITY SHALL NOT APPLY TO LIABILITY FOR DEATH OR PERSONAL INJURY RESULTING FROM SUCH PARTY'S NEGLIGENCE TO THE EXTENT APPLICABLE LAW PROHIBITS SUCH LIMITATION. SOME JURISDICTIONS DO NOT&lt;br /&gt;ALLOW THE EXCLUSION OR LIMITATION OF INCIDENTAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, SO THAT EXCLUSION AND LIMITATION MAY NOT APPLY TO YOU. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;10. U.S. GOVERNMENT END USERS. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;The Covered Code is a ``commercial item,'' as that term is defined in 48 C.F.R. 2.101 (Oct. 1995), consisting of ``commercial computer software'' and ``commercial computer software documentation,'' as such terms are used in 48 C.F.R. 12.212 (Sept. 1995). Consistent with 48 C.F.R. 12.212 and 48 C.F.R. 227.7202-1 through 227.7202-4 (June 1995), all U.S. Government End Users acquire Covered Code with only those rights set forth herein. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;11. MISCELLANEOUS. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;This License represents the complete agreement concerning subject matter hereof. If any provision of this License is held to be unenforceable, such provision shall be reformed only to the extent necessary to make it enforceable. This License shall be governed by California law provisions (except to the extent applicable law, if any, provides otherwise), excluding its conflict-of-law provisions. With respect to disputes in which at least one party is a citizen of, or an entity chartered or registered to do business in, the United States of America: (a) unless otherwise agreed in writing, all disputes relating to this License (excepting any dispute relating to intellectual property rights) shall be subject to final and binding arbitration, with the losing party paying all costs of arbitration; (b) any arbitration relating to this Agreement shall be held in Santa Clara County, California, under the auspices of JAMS/EndDispute; and (c) any litigation relating to this Agreement shall be subject to the jurisdiction of the Federal Courts of the Northern District of California, with venue lying in Santa Clara County, California, with the losing party responsible for costs, including without limitation, court costs and reasonable attorneys fees and expenses. The application of the United Nations Convention on Contracts for the International Sale of Goods is expressly excluded. Any law or regulation which provides that the language of a contract shall be construed against the drafter shall not apply to this License. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;12. RESPONSIBILITY FOR CLAIMS. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;Except in cases where another Contributor has failed to comply with Section 3.4, You are responsible for damages arising, directly or indirectly, out of Your utilization of rights under this License, based on the number of copies of Covered Code you made available, the revenues you received from utilizing such rights, and other relevant factors. You agree to work with affected parties to distribute responsibility on an equitable basis. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;EXHIBIT A. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;``The contents of this file are subject to the Mozilla Public License Version 1.0 (the &quot;License&quot;); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at http://www.mozilla.org/MPL/ &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;Software distributed under the License is distributed on an &quot;AS IS&quot; basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations under the License. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;The Original Code is ______________________________________. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;The Initial Developer of the Original Code is ________________________. Portions created by ______________________ are Copyright (C) ______  _______________________. All Rights Reserved. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;     Contributor(s): ______________________________________.'' &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1064151535</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1064151535</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1064151535</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Mozilla License 1.0</title>
		<created>1064151535</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="979" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;P&gt;Just use the search form on the right to select the persons you want to have more information on. You should at least use one of the search criteria.&lt;/P&gt;

&lt;P&gt;Please write an email to &lt;A href=&quot;mailto:minfo@mmbase.org&quot;&gt;info@mmbase.org&lt;/A&gt;, if you want to be added to the &quot;People at MMBase&quot;.&lt;/P&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1065432540</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>On&amp;nbsp;this page you can find information on people of the MMBase community.</intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1065432540</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>People at MMBase</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="981" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1066079640</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>Hola, we are working hard on the 1.9 release of MMBase. Please checkout the latest news articles for a status update or join the irc channel.



&lt;h4&gt;Documentation&lt;/h4&gt;

The most current MMBase docs are irregularly uploaded to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mmbase.org/mmdocs/&quot;&gt;www.mmbase.org/mmdocs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mmbase.org/api/&quot;&gt;www.mmbase.org/api&lt;/a&gt;. Pointing to the most current documentation of several of its features and the javadocs. Older versions are listed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mmbase.org/?portal=199&amp;page=549&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.</intro>
		<offline>1066079640</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1066079640</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Developers</title>
		<created>1066079698</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="987" owner="admin">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1068305400</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>MMBase is an object relational mapping tool to build advanced web-applications. If you are looking for an MMBase-style Enterprise Web Content Management System, please go to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cmscontainer.org&quot;&gt;CMScontainer.org&lt;/a&gt;. Both have strong multi media features and the CMScontainer has advanced portal functionalities (JSR 168 compliant). There is a large installed base in The Netherlands. Many of the largest Dutch sites/portals (Kennisnet, KNMI, broadcasters) use MMBase and/or the CMSContainer. Main characteristics: Java, Open Source, open standards. The systems can be used with all major operating systems, application servers and many different databases. Some of the users can be found below (latest sites build...).</intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1068305400</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="989" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1068305323</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>The goal of the MMBase Foundation is to facilitate the content management system MMBase for Open Source usage, along with its community, focusing on the stabilization, innovation and continuity of the software. The Foundation support collaboration between it's partners, to avoid redundant development. 



The MMBase Foundation supports the community: users, commercial partners and developers. The Foundation primarily looks after the interests of the users and commercial partners, as the developers have their own organisation structure, but supports the developers where and if necessary.</intro>
		<offline>1735686043</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1068305323</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Foundation</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="991" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;P&gt;The MMBase Foundation is a non-profit organization that is funded by partners. The Foundation partners can be divided in three groups; end users of MMBase, commercial partners that specialize in implementation and MMBase maintenance and hosting partners. &lt;/P&gt;

&lt;p&gt;



&lt;P&gt;You can find a list of our partners on the homepage. To contact one of them, click on their logo. 



&lt;P&gt;If you would like to know more about a partnership, please contact the Foundation at +31 (0)35 6288088 (gmt+1) or send an email to Jo@mmbase.org 

&lt;P&gt;&lt;/P&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1068319680</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>In the near future, this page will list all the partners of the Foundation, their portfolios, projects and company description.</intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1068319680</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Partners</title>
		<created>1073390459</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="997" owner="default">
		<body>The Foundation is in many cases the first contact point for new users and developers and coordinates the communication within the community. The Foundation also brings users and potential users together, so they can learn from each others experiences. Technical developments are collected and shared with partners and shared development between users is initiated by the Foundation. &lt;p&gt;



The Foundation plays a crucial role in gathering a critical mass of Open Source users, necessary for the future existence of Open Source and MMBase. Furthermore it informs companies, institutes and the government on why and how to use Open Source and how to maintain Open Source Software.  &lt;p&gt;



The Foundation has collaborated very actively with national and local governments of the Netherlands, in drawing up the basis of Open Source Software development plans for the Dutch public sector. There is a firm relation with the OSSOS program (Open Standards and Open Source Software) of the Dutch government, set up to improve the exchange of knowledge and components sources in governmental domains. The Foundation however addresses both the public and private sector. The MMBase Foundation offers a portal with information, a knowledgebase and information on best practices, as well as a suppliers list. &lt;p&gt;



The MMBase Foundation considers itself an international organisation; Open Source Software by nature is not bound to any boundaries. For that reason our website is English only, as is most of our communication.&lt;p&gt;



Other activities&lt;br&gt;

- Advisor of national and local governments on Open Standards and Open Source and advises on rules and regulations. &lt;br&gt;

- The Foundation actively informs politicians (European Parliament Members and Dutch national MPs) on the importance of open standards, OSS and software patent issues. &lt;br&gt;

- On the international level, the Foundation looks for cooperation with other communities, to share knowledge, applications and stimulate research and the Take Up of Open Source Software, especially MMBase. &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1068637640</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>The stability of a Open Source community depends on the stability and activity of its members.</intro>
		<offline>1735686021</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1068637640</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Activities within the MMBase Community</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1001" owner="default">
		<body>The MMBase Foundation was established in 2002. It is a non profit institute and its main objective, as established in article 2 of the Foundation Statutes, is to facilitate the Content Management System MMBase for Open Source use, with the related community, focusing on stability, innovation and the existence of the software. &lt;p&gt;



MMBase is a so called enterprise web content management system, covering the full range from hard authentication, full functional large scale web-maintenance to personalised e-learning environments. The MMBase Foundation supports the community: users, commercial partners and developers. The developers have their own portal and organisation structure, their Management Committee advises the Foundation. The Foundation primarily looks after the interests of the users and commercial partners, but supports the developers where and if necessary. Major goal is to facilitate the web content management system for Open Source use with a focus on stabilization, innovation and continuity of the software and community. The MMBase Foundation also plays an important role in creating awareness, promoting and informing the public on Open Source Software, until now mainly in the Netherlands.&lt;p&gt;



At this point the Foundation has a few dozen (commercial) partners. There is a large developers community, of which 12 have the status of committer and another 5 form the MMBase Management Committee. The MMBase Foundation has a CEO a part-time employees, a board and an advisory committee of partners and developers (the MMC), and users. MMBase is the largest Open Source Community in the Netherlands and plays a leading role in the overall Open Source application and component development. The Foundation is so far- using quite informal methods for the evaluation of the implementation partners and hosting providers.</body>
		<lastmodified>1279733894</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator>admin</creator>
		<online>1068810660</online>
		<author>Jo</author>
		<title>About the MMBase Foundation</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier>admin</lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1003" owner="default">
		<body>The origin of MMBase was developed in the heart of the Dutch Public Broadcasting organization VPRO  (www.vpro.nl). After 5 years of internal development, the VPRO decided to make MMBase Open Source in May of the year 2000. Soon other broadcasters also started to use MMBase as well and a year later there where already a handful MMBase websites. &lt;p&gt;



After the first year the take-up got into another gear and at this moment there are as far as we know- several hundreds MMBase websites. We have even found some in China (not that we understand what they are about). And the number of users that consider MMBase to be strategically important for their organization is growing fast. From an easy to use CMS just for the presentation of some web pages, the system is now turning in to an enterprise system.</body>
		<lastmodified>1068810907</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686007</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1068810907</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase history</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1005" owner="default">
		<body>This means that MMBase can be used to manage information with only one tool: a web-browser. Information can time and place independent be created, stored, changed, manipulated and deleted. The editor needs no knowledge of technology. This of course only if you have the right authorisation to do so. MMbase separates content from lay-out and structure. This means, for example, that a piece of text can be used on different sites, mobile phones, flash movies, print, CD, in a different context and lay out. If the text itself would contain lay-out properties, it would be very difficult to accomplish this, if possible at all. &lt;p&gt;



MMBase is an object-oriented system. This means that information pages normally consists of several objects, for example: picture, text, location, audio, etcetera. Each of these objects can be re-used many times, on many different channels. Nevertheless, an object is stored only once in the database. If the object changes, the changes will immediately be visible on all devices. So if the opening time of the library of your organisation changes, you don't have to check all websites where this information was once copied to. Most CMS are not object oriented, but document oriented. These systems are fine if you want to store documents 'as they are', but they are poor in avoiding redundancy of information. Just imagine the amount of documents that has to be checked if e.g. the postal adres of a large company changes.  &lt;p&gt;



MMbase is build in Java, and uses open standards for information exchange (XML) and storage.  Perhaps the most important characteristic of MMBase is that it is platform independent. This means that the choice for an operating system is free (e.g. Linux, Unix, Windows), as is the choice for a database (e.g. Informix, DB2, MSSQL, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle) or application server. MMBase will in future move towards the J2EE platform. &lt;p&gt;



MMBase can be used in any language. All major documentation is in English, as is the MMBase website. MMBase supports complex workflow and authorisation matrices (for personalization), the creation of new sections in a website, creation of forms, etc. MMBase is very flexible and adapts easily to the demands of an organisation.&lt;p&gt;



MMBase is a professional system. To implement MMBase knowledge of setting up a server, database, application server and installing software is necessary. In most cases an implementation partner will do the job. However, after installation, no technical know how is necessary for the maintenance of information, or re-arranging the navigation, or adding new sections to your website.&lt;p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1068811136</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>MMBase is a so called dynamic enterprise web content management system (CMS).</intro>
		<offline>1735686056</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1068811136</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase in a nutshell</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1007" owner="default">
		<body>To facilitate the content managementsystem MMBase the MMBase Foundation has developed a number of product for the promotion of MMBase. Users and distributors can order or get these products at the MMBase Foundation. &lt;p&gt;



The products available at this time are:&lt;p&gt;



&lt;u&gt;The MMok&lt;/u&gt;: a large MMBase coffee cup.&lt;br&gt;

&lt;u&gt;The MMBase pen&lt;/u&gt;: a red and gold pen&lt;br&gt;

&lt;u&gt;The MMBase brochure&lt;/u&gt;: the MMBase brochure. Both available in English and Dutch. &lt;p&gt;



Please contact the Foundation for more information on availability +31 (0)35 6288088 or info@mmbase.org.</body>
		<lastmodified>1069144800</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1069144800</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase promotion products</title>
		<created>1070980917</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle>The MMBase Foundation develops promotion material for MMBase distributors and users</subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1011" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1069855270</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>A large white and blue MMBase coffee cup.</intro>
		<offline>1735686010</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1069855270</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMok</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1015" owner="default">
		<body>The stand will be used for the promotion of MMBase and its supporting companies. The MMBase Foundation will use the stand for events and seminars, preferrably together with partners. If the Foundation is not using the stand, partners of the Foundation can use the stand for their own promotion activities. &lt;p&gt;



The stand exists of 12 boards that are inter-exchangable. The boards can be ordered separately and printed as desired. &lt;p&gt;



Please call the Foundation, for information on availability: +31 (0)35 6288088&lt;p&gt;



ATTENTION: This stand was initially developed for the CMS-congres, on the 24th of November 2003. The logos on the stand are the partners that participated on this day. The logo's on the stand are not permanant and can be changed.</body>
		<lastmodified>1069860799</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>The MMBase Foundation has aquired a stand for promotion purposes.</intro>
		<offline>1735686079</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1069860799</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase stand</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1017" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;p&gt;MMBase Foundation&lt;br /&gt;

Neuweg 83&lt;br /&gt;

1214 GM Hilversum&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

The Netherlands&lt;br /&gt;

T: +31 (0)35 6838770 or +31 (0)6 53292887&lt;br /&gt;

E: please use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mmbase.org/email&quot;&gt;email form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;CEO&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jo Lahaye&lt;br /&gt;

Mobile: +31 (0)6 53292887&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 

  For general information about the use of MMBase, RFI's, courses, subscription 

  to the Newsletter, presentations, partnerships and questions related to the 

  Foundation please phone: +31-35-6838770 (gmt+1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;?portal=202&amp;amp;page=41151&quot;&gt;Mailinglists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For information about the developers community and the development of MMBase we encourage you to post your general or more specific questions to one of our &lt;a href=&quot;?portal=202&amp;amp;page=41151&quot;&gt;mailinglists&lt;/a&gt;, for example to the users or developers list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:website@mmbase.org&quot;&gt;website@mmbase.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

  For remarks on the MMBase web site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;IRC #mmbase&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For discussions about technical issues, technical questions, or just to chat 

  with MMBase developers. There is a IRC channel that you can join: please drop by at &lt;a href=&quot;irc://irc.slashnet.org/#mmbase&quot;&gt;#mmbase&lt;/a&gt;, that is at irc.slashnet.org. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Twitter&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, developers may twitter to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mmbase&quot;&gt;@mmbase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;.</body>
		<lastmodified>1070618820</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1070618820</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1070618820</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Contact information</title>
		<created>1070618867</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1019" owner="default">
		<body>Specifications Philips bSure XG2	&lt;p&gt;



Techniek	: 3 x PSI		&lt;br&gt;

Resolution	: 1024 x 768 (XGA)	 &lt;br&gt;

Light	        : 1500 ANSI Lumen 	&lt;br&gt;

Weight 	        : 3,7 kg		&lt;br&gt;

Lens	        : Zoom/ Focus	&lt;br&gt;

Contrast	        : 300:1&lt;br&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1070980393</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>The Foundation has a Philips bSure XG2 beamer available for partners.</intro>
		<offline>1070980393</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1070980393</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBeamer</title>
		<created>1070980386</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle>Philips bSure XG2</subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1023" owner="default">
		<body>Size 100 x 75 cm.&lt;br&gt;



The Foundation has two PCV MMBase promotion boards available for partners. The boards can be used at congresses or for example presentation. 

&lt;p&gt;

Please contact the Foundation for more information: +31 (0)35 6288088 or info@mmbase.org</body>
		<lastmodified>1071761214</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1071761214</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1071761214</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase hardboards</title>
		<created>1071761194</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1027" owner="default">
		<body>This page shows the minutes of the MMBase Committers meeting (previously called the MMBase Management Committee). If you have some input for a MMC meeting, please sent an email to developers@mmbase.org



Overview:</body>
		<lastmodified>1081502640</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1081502640</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1081502640</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMC Minutes</title>
		<created>1081502664</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1039" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;p&gt;

For information in English, please contact the Foundation (Jo@mmbase.org)&lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;



10.00 Opening. &lt;br&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Jo Lahaye&lt;/b&gt;, directeur Stichting MMBase&lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

10.05 Welkomswoord TU Delft&lt;br&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Drs. Ruben van Wendel de Joode, onderzoeker TU Delft. &lt;/b&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

	&lt;b&gt; &lt;i&gt; Overheid&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/i&gt; &lt;br&gt;

10.10 &lt;b&gt;Arjen Hof&lt;/b&gt;, programmamanager innovatie Amsterdam, presenteert mede namens Leeuwarden en Egem, de samenwerkingsplannen van en voor gemeenten. &lt;br&gt;Open standaarden, open source. 

&lt;b&gt;Mark Bressers&lt;/b&gt;, programmamanager OSOSS. Wat is na 1,5 jaar bereikt en wat zijn de ambities voor dit jaar.&lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

             &lt;b&gt; &lt;i&gt; Onderwijs &lt;/b&gt; &lt;/i&gt; &lt;br&gt;

10.45 &lt;b&gt;Fred de Vries&lt;/b&gt;, Open Universiteit Nederland, doet onderzoek naar open source systemen voor het hoger onderwijs, in opdracht van de digitale universiteit. Een tussentijds verslag. Een aantal ROC's zocht een manier om met studenten aan de maritieme opleiding in contact te blijven tijdens het langdurige verblijf op zee. Ordina en The Mediator Group vonden een oplossing met behulp van Didactor.&lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

11.25 Koffiepauze&lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

             &lt;b&gt; &lt;i&gt; OSS en de industrie. &lt;/b&gt; &lt;/i&gt; &lt;br&gt;

11.45 &lt;b&gt;Dr. Frank van der Linden&lt;/b&gt;, van Philips Medical systems, over de ervaringen van Philips met het beheer van wereldwijd gebruikte software voor medische systemen. &lt;br&gt;

12.05 &lt;b&gt;Bernd Taselaar&lt;/b&gt;, Nederland ICT, directeur Fenit (Federatie Nederlandse IT) over de opstelling van zijn achterban ten aanzien van open standaarden en open source. &lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

12.25 Lunchpauze&lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

13.15 &lt;b&gt;Dick Rijken&lt;/b&gt;, voorzitter Stichting MMBase, welkomswoord voor de middag, kort overzicht activiteiten en plannen. &lt;br&gt;

13.25 &lt;b&gt;Pierre van Rooden&lt;/b&gt;, MMBase Management &lt;br&gt;Committee (MMC). Nieuw MMC, toeksomtvisie, release 1.7 en plannen voor release 1.8. &lt;br&gt;

13.35 &lt;b&gt;Henk Hangyi &lt;/b&gt;(MMatch). Diverse showcases, e-commerce en een overzicht van functionaliteit die open source wordt aangeboden. &lt;br&gt;

13.55 &lt;b&gt;Bruno Felix &lt;/b&gt;(Submarine, St. Web in de wijk) presenteert MMBob, een prachtig MMBase-style forum dat aan de MMBase-community wordt aangeboden. &lt;br&gt;

14.10 &lt;b&gt;Andres Steijaert&lt;/b&gt;. Surfnet presenteert zijn geavanceerde MMBase-applicatie. Deze applicatie is ontwikkeld door Finalist IT Group en Q42 en gebaseerd op de applicatie die voor Leeuwarden is ontwikkeld.&lt;br&gt;

14.20 &lt;b&gt;Kars Veling&lt;/b&gt;: Qstats. Nieuwe kijk op managementinformatie.&lt;br&gt; 

&lt;br&gt;

14.30 Parallelsessies&lt;br&gt;

1. Zoeken en vinden. &lt;br&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Henny Bekker&lt;/b&gt;. Een nieuwe zoekengine voor Surfnet.&lt;br&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Henk Hangyi&lt;/b&gt;, zoeken en vinden binnen MMBase. &lt;br&gt;

2. Is MMBase het juiste CMS voor mij&lt;br&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Fokke Kooistra &lt;/b&gt;laat zien hoe MMBase in de dagelijkse pratijk bij de EO werkt en hoe het ook in uw omgeving kan passen. &lt;br&gt;

3. Wetenschappelijke workshop&lt;br&gt;

Discussie onder leiding van &lt;b&gt;Rob Peters&lt;/b&gt; en &lt;b&gt;Ruben Wendel de Joode&lt;/b&gt;.

&lt;b&gt;Daniel Ockeloen&lt;/b&gt;, een van de architecten van MMBase presenteert kort de uitdaging van MMBase om applicaties die her en der gebouwd worden uitwisselbaar te houden. &lt;b&gt;Auke Jilderda&lt;/b&gt; van Philips Research presenteert de ideeen van Philips over de open source manier (consolidatie) versus de formele manier (pre-deployment definition) en wat dit voor zijn organisatie betekent. De discussie gaat over dit spanningsveld: Wat zijn de issues voor bedrijven die in open source applicaties ontwikkelen en waar moeten ze op de langere termijn rekening mee houden. Ruben en Rob presenteren kort de grote wetenschappelijke onderzoeksvoorstellen die op dit gebied in de maak zijn. 

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

15.45 Pauze. &lt;br&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

16.05 &lt;b&gt;Angel Vaca&lt;/b&gt;, Directie Fundecyt, Extremadura, Spanje. &lt;br&gt;Over het succes van open source (LinEx) in een van de armere 'platteland' regios van Europa en de mogelijke samenwerking met de Stichting MMBase in een internationaal project. (English / Engels!) &lt;br&gt;

16.35 &lt;b&gt;Wim de Bie&lt;/b&gt;, over zijn populaire Bieslog&lt;br&gt;

17.00 Borrel&lt;br&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1084347240</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1084347240</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Program fourth MMEvent</title>
		<created>1084359349</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle>Program of the day [in Dutch]:</subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1047" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1087375906</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>Most of the presentations that are held on the MMBase Event are public and can be downloaded from this site. If you would like to receive a presentation that was held on the MMEvent4 that is not available on this page, please contact the Foundation.</intro>
		<offline>1735686046</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1087375906</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Presentations on the MMBase Event4</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1049" owner="default">
		<body>The MMBase community of users, developers, and implementators, and interested companies that visited the Event, did not only see how MMBase is currently used within governmental and educational institutes and businesses. Also a number of prominent companies like Philips Medical Systems shared their experiences with the use of open source and MMBase and the related policy questions. &lt;p&gt;

 

There were also end users, talking about the features and advantages of their MMBase applications. An enthusiastic end user like Wim de Bie proudly showed his Bieslog, a multimedia site with more than 200.000 unique visitors a month, on which he publishes at least three times a day. The website features text, film, video, sound and pictures. 

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Ruben van Wendel de Joode&lt;/b&gt;, researcher at the Technische Universiteit Delft opened the MMEvent4. The TU Delft is going to invest in open source research in the next few years and wants to work together with the MMBase community. Van Wendel de Joode studies open source communities and is enthusiastic about the Dutch open source developments and specifically about MMBase, with its CMS widely used within the public sector. 

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Marc Bressers&lt;/b&gt; is program manager of OSOSS (Open Standards en Open Source Software for the government), a platform for open source knowledge exchange. OSOSS works together with the MMBase community. MMBase is already used by many governmental institutions and many more are taking the use of MMBase into consideration, explains Bressers.

&lt;p&gt; 

According to Bressers some policy makers in governmental and educational institutions and companies are still prejudice against open source software. The general idea is that Open source software has an idealistic approach and that the software is not suitable for (semi-)commercial use. Changing this view is one of the major tasks of the OSOSS, which programmes inform governmental institutions about the use and development of open source applications

&lt;p&gt; 

Governmental institutions that use open source are, according to Bressers, generally positive and try to increase their participation in this field. The government policy on open source and ICT (as put forwared in the Vendrik resolution) has targeted to decreasing supplier dependency. Reasons for government institutions to use open source are diverse, varying from bad experiences with closed source software (vendor lock-ins) to the need for shared development. 

&lt;p&gt; 

Some institutions have unrealistically high expectations of open source software. Through consultancy, OSOSS aims for strong embedded open source standards, like CANOS (Nederlandse Catalogus van Open Standaarden).

&lt;p&gt; 

OSOSS: http://www.ososs.nl

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Joost van Stiphout&lt;/b&gt;, of the Electronic Municipality (EGEM), advises municipalities on ICT issues. EGEM notices a strong increasing interest in open source software amongst its members. One of the main risks of closed source software, when used by municipalities, is the loss of control over the use of information about its citizens.

&lt;p&gt; 

EGEM has constructed a project site for Dutch municipalities based on MMBase. This site makes it possible for municipalities to work together on projects; documents can be exchanged and forums maintained. The project site application will offered to the MMBase community. 

&lt;p&gt; 

EGEM: http://www.egem.nl. 

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Fred de Vries&lt;/b&gt;, Open University the Netherlands (OUNL), points out the general state of affaires regarding electronic learning systems. According to his findings, the needs concerning e-learning applications are generally developed and well defined only after purchasing software. Learning needs should define the choice for a system, not the other way around, he says. 

&lt;p&gt; 

The Open University researches open source electronic learning systems, under the authority of the Digital University in The Netherlands. The reports will be published in the course of this summer. MMBases e-learning system Didactor will also be taken along.

&lt;p&gt; 

The motive for conducting this research lies in the discussion about open content and intellectual property. In the Netherland and abroad, many educational institutes, foresee major problems concerning these issues (more information on the subject of open content and intellectual property can be found on: http://www.sakaiproject.org/ ). De Vries stresses the importance of increasing awareness of platform independency and the use of learning technological specifications like IMS and QTI.

&lt;p&gt; 

Nederlands Normalisatie Instituut: http://www.nen.nl/nl/act/spec/leertech

Surf Six expertisegrope: http://e-learning.surf.nl/six

Digitale Universiteit: http://www.digiuni.nl

Open Universiteit: http://www.ounl.nl

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Theo Wittering&lt;/b&gt;, Ordina, stresses that open source software offers users more transparency. Users of OS software have more influence on the process of development and innovation of the product. The development of open source systems is demand-oriented and easy to access.. 

&lt;p&gt; 

An example is Didactor, an electronic learning method, partly based on the MMBase engine. Didactor is developed by the EO, The Mediatorgroup, Finalist IT Group and is presently used by Den Haag and Amsterdam. 

&lt;p&gt; 

The Mediator Group: http://www.mediatorgroup.com

Didactor: http://www.didactor.nl

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Andres Steijaert &lt;/b&gt;is project leader at SURFnet, a co-operation between Dutch master and bachelor educational institutes. SURFnet comprises 150 organisations and about 750.000 users. After a thorough study of content management systems, SURFnet chose MMBase for their web development. They have built a new MMBase application, based on previous developments by the municipality of Leeuwarden en Kennisnet. Next to features like information management with a browser, workflow, version control, separation of layout and content, scheduling of messages, and content labelling (classification), the SURFnet CMS offers a real-time response forum, and a tool to define tailor made URLs.

&lt;p&gt; 

Surfnets choice for MMBase lies in the strong MMBase community. The SURFnet build application will soon be open source available. 

&lt;p&gt; 

Surfnet: http://www.surfnet.nl

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Frank van der Linden&lt;/b&gt;, Philips Medical Systems, notices a strong increase in the use of open source and the so called bounded community systems within Philip since 2003.

&lt;p&gt; 

Some of these open source systems are known to their clients, which in itself could be a reason to implement the open source product in Philips electronics. Philipss clients generally rate the use of open source products as positive. Another reason to use open source is the absence of licence fees, unlike closed source software. A third important reason for Philips to use open source is the prohibition by governments like China of the use of certain closed source software. 

&lt;p&gt; 

Questions concerning the use of open source software in respect to their own patents and also problems regarding liability in case of damage are aspects still discussed within Philips. After a corporate policy has been defined, Van der Linden expects the use of open source software within Philips to increase. 

&lt;p&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Dick Rijken&lt;/b&gt;, chairman of the MMBase Foundation, wants to stimulates users of MMBase to give more feedback. He explains that, thanks to the Publieke Omroep, there is new and improve MMBase documentation. Release 1.7 is the first release within the new approach of making the MMBase core lighter. Important issues for the future of MMBase are, according to him:&lt;br&gt;

- The relation between modules/ component and the MMBase core. &lt;br&gt;

- Limiting the scope: what is MMBase and what not, and how to deal with this? &lt;p&gt;

 

MMBase: http://www.mmbase.org&lt;p&gt;

 

&lt;b&gt;Pierre van Rooden&lt;/b&gt;, member of the MMBase Management Committee sees a number of tasks for the MMC (MMBase Management Committee): &lt;br&gt;

- keeping together the community of developers. &lt;br&gt;

- carrying out the opinions of the community of developers&lt;br&gt;

- developing a long term vision&lt;p&gt;

 

At this point, MMBase counts 16 committers and a group of active developers. Van Rooden requests all participants of the Event to bring their developers in contact with the MMBase community of developers. MMBase: http://www.mmbase.org

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Henk Hangyi&lt;/b&gt;, CEO of MMatch, opens the session of MMBase showcases. Hangyi announces a number of new developments: statistics, e-mails in HTML-format, imagemaps, etc.etc. He explains the strategie on these development. The community is also working on a peer-to-peer network for the MMBase packages. This way, all the MMBase packages and modules placed on different servers will be available and downloadable from the MMBase site, and therefore easier to find. 

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Bruno Felix&lt;/b&gt;, Submarine, developed a forum for web in de wijk in co-operation with Kennisnet. This forum offers inhabitants of a city an easy way to make their own webpages and publish them on the Internet. 

&lt;p&gt; 

Web in de Wijk: http://www.webindewijk.nl&lt;br&gt;

Submarine: http://www.submarine.nl

&lt;p&gt; 

PARALLELSESSIE I: scientific workshop &lt;br&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Margot Wijnen &lt;/b&gt;(Innovatieplatform), gives a short introduction at the scientific workshop. The Innovation Platform invites the MMBase community to write a report about the intended European legislation on software patents. What are the hindrances to software development and innovations according to the MMBase community?

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Daniel Ockeloen &lt;/b&gt;(MMBase developer), talks about the questions that the MMBase community is facing. For example, how to get synergy out of co-operation? Not the architecture of the software, but the architecture of the community is decisive, according to Ockeloen. The developers community is working to decrease and lighten the core of MMBase. The consequences according to Ockeloen are that the area around the core (the applications and packages) will become a gray area. Ockeloen prefers to see MMBase develop towards an end product. 

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Frank van der Linden &lt;/b&gt;(Philips medical systems), says that not all companies want to offer their components open source. Making software open source means also offering support and maintenance. Van der Linden presents the ideas of Philips on the open source way (consolidation) vs. the formal way (pre-deployment definion) and the consequences both options have for an organisation.

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;ngel Vaca &lt;/b&gt;(direction of Fundecyt, Extremadura, Spain). The province of Extremadura sees the stimulation of the use of information technology as the way to improve economic development of the region, one of the poorest regions in Europe. With their project LinEx, they have succeeded in giving more that 50% of the population access to a computer. Based on Linux, Extremadura developed user friendly software called LinEx, that is now distributed to all the computers in Extremadura. 

&lt;p&gt; 

ngel Vaca is also connected to ETHOS, the European Trust Platform for Homogenizing Open Source Software Efforts. ETHOS strives for the explanation of the rules for the production of components and the definitions of quality standards in the Free Open Source Industrie (FLOSS).

&lt;p&gt; 

Gnulinex: http://www.gnulinex.org

&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;b&gt;Wim de Bie &lt;/b&gt;(famous Dutch TV personality, VPRO) is the general editor of a weblog for the VPRO. He is an enthusiastic MMBase user, and publishes at least three times a day on his weblog called Bieslog. His multimedia Bieslog is developed with MMBase and contains many features, like an extensive archive on the site. De Bie also has plans for live broadcasting on his Bieslog. With more that 200.000 unique visitors per month, he has a very successful site. With a room full of smiling people, he managed to share his excitement and make this presentation a great closure of a successful and innovative MMBase day. 

&lt;p&gt; 

Bieslog: http://bieslog.vpro.nl

&lt;p&gt; 

For more information, please contact the Foundation, jo@mmbase.org , 035 6288088.&lt;p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1087378340</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>On June 9, some 100 attendees enjoyed a day full of presentations and debate at the Technical university of Delft.</intro>
		<offline>1735686020</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1087378340</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Successful fourth Event</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle>Hundred people visited fourth annual Event</subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1051" owner="default">
		<body>In the parallel session on Search and Find three different approaches on search on MMBase websites were presented: Fast, Lucene, and Database Search. In the discussion the solution with Lucene came out as the favourite, since it is open source and based on Java, which makes a seamless integration with MMBase possible.</body>
		<lastmodified>1087380824</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>Henny Bekker (Surfnet)&lt;br&gt;

Wouter Heijke (Finalist)&lt;br&gt;

Henk Hangyi (MMatch)&lt;br&gt;</intro>
		<offline>1735686044</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1087380824</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Search and Find</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1053" owner="default">
		<body>Presentation on the MMBase packages. Packages are add on functionalities for MMBase, like a poll and a forum. Currently a number of these packages can be downloaded from the MMBase site. But the development of a peer-to-peer package manager will make it possible to make packages from different servers available for all MMBase users.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1087381110</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>H.Hangyi</intro>
		<offline>1735686030</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1087381110</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase packages</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1055" owner="default">
		<body>Presentation on the generic MMBase forum. In cooperation with a number MMBase end users a MMBase forum is being developed. Bruno held a presentation on how this came to be and what they are developing.</body>
		<lastmodified>1087382149</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686049</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1087382149</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Bruno Felix</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1057" owner="default">
		<body>Fred de Vries held a presentation on the use of open source within the Open University.</body>
		<lastmodified>1087383544</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686004</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1087383544</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Fred de Vries</title>
		<created>-1</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1059" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088855108</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>If you have MMBase related presentations (video/powerpoint), please feel free to send them to info@mmbase.org and we will put them online. Currently we are making some introduction videos about how to use MMBase, how to install it, information about the editwizards, and much more.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;



Most of the presentations presented at this page come from previous MMEvents. Please be aware that these presentations are in Dutch.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;



If you watched a presentation and want to provide use with an abstract of that presentation, please feel free to sent the abstract to info@mmbase.org and we will put it on this page besides the presentation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;



Fave fun watching the videos !!!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</intro>
		<offline>1088855108</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088855108</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase presentations</title>
		<created>1088855141</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1061" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088855793</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>Presentation about Wiab by Arjen Hof.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

This presentation was recorded at the first MMBase event (Dutch).</intro>
		<offline>1088855793</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088855793</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Wiab</title>
		<created>1088855793</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1063" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088857574</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>This presentation was recorded during the first MMBase Event. Dick Rijken talked aabout what MMBase is, about the history of MMBase, and about why the VPRO made it open source.</intro>
		<offline>1088857574</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088857574</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Introduction about MMBase</title>
		<created>1088857574</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1065" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088859245</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>This presenation was recorded during the fist MMBase Event. Erwin Blom talked about...</intro>
		<offline>1088859245</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088859245</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Editorial people</title>
		<created>1088859245</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1067" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088860057</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>This presentation was recorded during the first MMBase event.</intro>
		<offline>1088860057</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088860057</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Technical Presenation</title>
		<created>1088860057</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1069" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088860252</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>This presentation was recorded during the first MMBase event. The first part of the presentation is missing.</intro>
		<offline>1088860252</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088860252</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Lowlands</title>
		<created>1088860252</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1071" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088860615</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1088860615</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088860615</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Jeroen</title>
		<created>1088860615</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1073" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088860689</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1088860689</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088860689</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Sanne</title>
		<created>1088860689</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1075" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088860773</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1088860773</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088860773</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Martijn</title>
		<created>1088860773</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1077" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088860935</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1088860935</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088860935</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Kars</title>
		<created>1088860935</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1079" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088860992</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1088860992</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088860992</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Gilion</title>
		<created>1088860992</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1081" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1088861046</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1088861046</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1088861046</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>JeanLuc</title>
		<created>1088861046</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1083" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;p&gt;

The MMBase Foundation was set up by end users and is now supported by end users and commercial implementation companies. The present partners can be found on the homepage. Joining us, means we can put a greater effort in working together, sharing code and knowledge. For a few thousand euro's a year, we can achieve more.  So please help.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

If you want to become a partner of the MMBase Foundation to support the community, please contact the director of the Foundation, Jo Lahaye, by sending an email to Jo@MMBase.org or phone (GMT+1) +31 (0)35 6288088.&lt;/p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1089200520</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1089200520</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Partner contracts</title>
		<created>1094049595</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1087" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1089878580</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>This presentation made by Henk Hangyi shows how to install MMBase in 20 minutes. Henk will guide you through the installation of the JDK, an application server, a database and finally MMBase. After watching this you will be able to run MMBase.</intro>
		<offline>1089878580</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1089878580</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Installing MMBase in 20 minutes (English)</title>
		<created>1089878598</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1089" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1090225159</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>In this session Henk Hangyi will guide you through the proces of making your own MMBase object cloud. This proces involves: Short explication of objects and relations. How you define MMBase objects, introducation of some standard MMBase objects, creating/updating/deleting objects. How to create relations in MMBase.</intro>
		<offline>1090225159</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1090225159</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Working with the MMBase object cloud (English)</title>
		<created>1090225159</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1091" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;p&gt;

By selecting the first checkbox you declare that you have read and understood The Mozilla Public License version 1.1. that can be found on http://www.mozilla.org/MPL/ and that you accept all consequences that derive from this license. This download may only be used in a way that meets the requirements of MPL 1.1. 

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;

Although the MPL 1.1. rules out any responsibility and liability concerning the implementation and use of LeoCMS, we ask you to declare explicitly, by selecting the second checkbox, that the city of Leeuwarden will under no circumstances be held responsible for the consequences that derive from the download, installation or use of LeoCMS. Otherwise, do not continue. 

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;

Please click the button below (download) if you agree on the terms and conditions mentioned above to start the download. And please be sure to mention these requirements when distributing any sources of LeoCMS. 

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;

We think LeoCMS offers you a very sophisticated Web Content Management System with some portal technology. Enjoy! 

&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;

If you want, you can leave your name and e-mailadres. We will be glad to keep you informed on updates and changes. Or perhaps you would even be interested in further development yourself. The MMBase Foundation thanks the city of Leeuwarden for offering LeoCMS to the community and Finalist IT Group for building the application and their help with this open source release. 

&lt;/p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1102795440</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>Please read the information on this page carefully, before starting the download of the MMBase-style LeoCMS-application offered as open source software by the city of Leeuwarden. The application and documentation is mainly in Dutch (we will work on an English version).</intro>
		<offline>1449864240</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1102795440</online>
		<author>andre</author>
		<title>LeoCMS-application</title>
		<created>1102795466</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1093" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_announcemail&quot;&gt;Announce&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Regular news updates&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/announce&quot;&gt;subscribe/unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; |

&lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_announcemail&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt; 

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_developersmail&quot;&gt;Developers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The 'developers' list. This list is used by the MMBase developers, it contains technical discussions, votes and development related questions.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/developers&quot;&gt;subscribe/unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_developersmail&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_usersmail&quot;&gt;Users&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

The 'users' or 'frontend' list. This list contains discussions related to the developing of templates and other front-end related issues. Besides that it may function as a discussion list for all things concerning the MMBase community.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/users&quot;&gt;subscribe/unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; | 

  &lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_usersmail&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_cvsmail&quot;&gt;CVS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

  Shows all MMBase cvs changes (daily mail)&lt;br /&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/cvs&quot;&gt;subscribe/unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; |

  &lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_cvsmail&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Archives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community (not active)&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_communitymail&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Committers&lt;/a&gt; (not active)&lt;br /&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;index.jsp?page=page_committorsmail&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1106602680</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>The first step to get involved with MMBase, subscribe to one of the mailingslists. The mailinglists are maintained by the MMC.</intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1106602680</online>
		<author>andre</author>
		<title>MMBase mailingslists</title>
		<created>1107987747</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1095" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/developers&quot;&gt;Subscribe or unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; to this list.</body>
		<lastmodified>1106604660</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1106604660</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Developers mailing list</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1097" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/users&quot;&gt;Subscribe or unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; to this list.</body>
		<lastmodified>1106604960</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1106604960</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Users mailing list</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1099" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/announce&quot;&gt;Subscribe or unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; to this list.</body>
		<lastmodified>1106605020</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1106605020</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Announce mailing list</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1101" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/cvs&quot;&gt;Subscribe or unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; to this list.</body>
		<lastmodified>1107979560</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1107979560</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>SCM mailing list</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1103" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1107979620</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1107979620</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Community mailing list</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1105" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1108416540</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>Here you'll find the latest official MMBase release, builds from the stable branch - like MMBase 1.8 beta - and the HEAD branch from cvs. Besides that this page lists several MMBase based applications and packages.</intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1108416540</online>
		<author>andre</author>
		<title>Download releases, builds and applications</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1107" owner="admin">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1112606220</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1112606220</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Committers mailinglist</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1109" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;p&gt;

The foundation offers a contract to companies or persons who want to become a partner. This contract formalizes the partnership and contains a mutual code of conduct.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

It is now possible to download the english version of the commercial vendor partner contract.

&lt;/p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1118670720</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1118670720</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>How to become a partner</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1111" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1118673000</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>Examples of websites build with MMBase</intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1118673000</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Websites in MMBase</title>
		<created>1144825367</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1113" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;p&gt;Since its start in 2003 the main purpose of the foundation is to support the MMbase community as well as acting in the interest of users, commercial vendors and the developers community. Open source software is about working together, sharing, distributing, projectmanagemtn, maintaining sites, and software, etc. To coordinate these activities, the MMBase Foundation was established. Of course, the Foundation needs money to fullfill the coordinative task. If you would considermaking a contribution, please contact Jo Lahaye (Jo@mmbase.org).

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The goal of the MMBase Foundation is to facilitate the content management system MMBase for Open Source usage, along with its community, focusing on the stabilisation, innovation and continuity of the software. The foundation supports collaboration between its partners, to avoid redundant development.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The MMbase Foundation is of interest for those organisations that consider information technology, and especially MMBase, a valuable asset for their business, at this moment and in the future. If you consider a web interface as one of the primary tools to reach (potential) clients, you will understand that it is of great importance that the interface is flexible enough to grow with the ever changing demands of your business. This means continuous investments in applications. The foundation aims as much as possible to realise synergy in the development and maintenance of MMBase. The foundation helps organisations with requests for proposals (RFP) and offers information on service level agreements (SLA). Besides this it helps with the release of applications, modules and components. All components that have been developed within the community will get the same license as the MMBase core (Mozilla Public License 1.0) when released.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

The Foundation makes sure that the developers community gets as much as possible relevant information about user demands. On a regular basis the foundation organises meetings where end-users and commercial vendors can exchange thoughts and discuss new developments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Another important activity of the foundation is giving information concerning the chances and possibilities of open source software. We trie to prevent that for example the same functions are being developed at the same time by different people. Organisations can get actively involved in those developments. Organisations can steer these developments in a way that can be a benefit for their own business. In this arrangement we expect that our partners fully respect the open source software mindset and understand that the pioneers of MMBase heavily invested in development.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

For more information please contact the managing director of the foundation MMBase Mr. Jo Lahaye by email (jo@mmbase.org) or telephone (+31 (0)35 6288088).

&lt;/p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified>1119252660</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1119252660</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Why should you become a partner?</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1115" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1119359940</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1119359940</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Holland Open Software Conference 2005</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1117" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<lastmodified>1140619680</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>Contact the MMBase foundation for general information about the use of MMBase or for more specific questions.</intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1140619680</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>E-mail form</title>
		<created>1172084831</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1119" owner="default">
		<body>In the year 2005 a lot of people and organizations participated in the debate on the future of MMBase. There were -and are- many different views on the road ahead. In the autumn of 2005 this led to the conclusion that if we want to move ahead, we need a board that represents the whole community: developers, users and technical partners.



At the annual meeting of the MMBase Foundation (December 2005) a concrete proposal to install a technical board (in Dutch 'het technisch comit') was discussed and approved.



The developers proposed two candidates, as did the users and technical partners.These persons represent their colleagues. The Foundation acts as host and guides the process. The members of the technical board are (on behalf of):

-developers: Michiel Meeuwissen and Johannes Verelst;

-users: Ronald Vendelmans (Amsterdam), Arjan van Krimpen / Rob de Bruin (Kennisnet);

-service providers: Martijn Verhoeven (MAG Productions), Henk Hangyi (Finalist);

-foundation: Jo Lahaye.



For an overview of the MMBase Community see http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase/images/50545



This pages shows an overview of the minutes of meeting of the technical board:</body>
		<lastmodified>1151524860</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1151524860</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1151524860</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>MMBase Technical Board</title>
		<created>1151524871</created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1121" owner="default">
		<body>The MMBase community nows two groups that meet on a regular basis: (1) the tecnical board and (2) the MMBase Committers meeting (previously called the MMBase Management Committee). Next to these meeting the developers organize developers meetings to discuss ongoing projects and new initiatives. Once a year an MMBase Annual meeting is organized by the MMBase foundation.



The image in the left column gives a schematic overview of the mmbase community.</body>
		<lastmodified>1164395280</lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline>1735686000</offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online>1164395280</online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Regular meetings within the MMBase community</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1125" owner="default">
		<body>The current release of MMBase is version 1.9.</body>
		<lastmodified></lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>This page lists the current and all former Java docs of MMBase.</intro>
		<offline></offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online></online>
		<author></author>
		<title>API documentation</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1127" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;p&gt;Most documentation can be found in '&lt;a href=&quot;/mmdocs&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/a&gt;'. It lists the documentation that is available in docbook format in MMBase cvs from where it can be generated to html and pdf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The API documentation lists the Java docs of several releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mmdocs&quot;&gt;Current documentation (1.9)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/development/api/1.8/overview-summary.html&quot;&gt;MMBase ApiDocs 1.8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/development/api/1.7/overview-summary.html&quot;&gt;MMBase ApiDocs 1.7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/development/api/1.6/overview-summary.html&quot;&gt;MMBase ApiDocs 1.6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/development/api/1.5/overview-summary.html&quot;&gt;MMBase ApiDocs 1.5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/development/api/1.4/overview-summary.html&quot;&gt;MMBase ApiDocs 1.4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/principles&quot;&gt;Principle Tracker&lt;/a&gt; is a tool to keep track of several MMBase coding principles and provides guidelines to application development and development in general for and with MMBase.&lt;/p&gt;</body>
		<lastmodified></lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>The documentation of MMBase is devided in several parts.</intro>
		<offline></offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online></online>
		<author></author>
		<title>About the documentation</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1129" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.mmbase.org/mailman/listinfo/cmscontainer&quot;&gt;Subscribe or unsubscribe&lt;/a&gt; to this list.</body>
		<lastmodified></lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro></intro>
		<offline></offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online></online>
		<author></author>
		<title>CMS Container mailing list</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

	<node number="1131" owner="default">
		<body>To access MMBase's Subversion repository anonymously you must of course have svn installed.&lt;br /&gt; 

The URL is: https://scm.mmbase.org/ &lt;br /&gt;

It can be used on the command line: 'svn co https://scm.mmbase.org/mmbase/trunk' for guest access but when you want to check in, svn will request a name and password. MMBase developers or committers can use their original CVS pserver account. Otherwise contact the developers-list and we'll help you.&lt;br /&gt;

The history of our repository can be browsed at http://scm.mmbase.org/view/</body>
		<lastmodified></lastmodified>
		<show>true</show>
		<intro>MMBase uses Subversion as its content repository since May 1st, 2009.</intro>
		<offline></offline>
		<creator></creator>
		<online></online>
		<author></author>
		<title>Subversion</title>
		<created></created>
		<lastmodifier></lastmodifier>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
	</node>

</articles>
