<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<news exportsource="mmbase://alfred.mmbase.org/mmweb/foundation" timestamp="20131003164110">
	<node number="13321" owner="admin">
		<body>In november 2003 a lot of people, especially developers will be working on the site. This may cause some inconvenience now and then, thank you in advance for your understanding.
The new site has been built under supervision of Rob Vermeulen in cooperation with a lot of developers and the Foundation.</body>
		<title>New developers site deployed</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Although we're still working on a lot of features and pages, we've decided to present the new site.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="13536" owner="import">
		<body>More than 2500 government services combined in one website. MMBase makes it happen.

Looking for subsidies or licenses? From now on everybody can use the Dutch Government site (www.overheid.nl) for these issues, with more than 2500 services online. For this purpose the site has been completely redesigned, and rebuild in MMBase. The services are offered at the so called Government counter and are organized according to the principles of the well know
Dutch website; startpagina (starting page).

The counter leads the visitor to the correct government site, with more detailed information on the subject. They are also informed about the availability of electronic forms and the services that can (already) be used online.

The counter is not the only innovation. The sophisticated developed search engine unlocks information on all government sites, now over 1200. The site also contains a law bank that is accessible for everybody without cost.

The MMBase build www.overheid.nl is visited 12.000 times a day and is developed and contained by www.advies.overheid.nl assigned by the Ministry of Internal Affairs. The Ministry of Economic Affaires is co-initiator and client of the government counter. The sites are part of ICTU, the
organization for government and ICT.

Source: http://www.overheid.nl
</body>
		<title>2500 services combined in one website</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Looking for subsidies or licenses? From now on everybody can use the Dutch government site (www.overheid.nl) for these issues, with more than 2500 services online.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="13544" owner="import">
		<body>MMBase 1.6.5 is released, shortly after the 1.6.4 release. This is because MMBase-1.6.4 contains a wrong class wich may result in rather confusing output of some queries. Check out the releasenotes for more information. 

Please update your mmbase.jar if you're already using MMBase-1.6.4.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.6.5 is released</title>
		<subtitle>MMBase 1.6.5 is released</subtitle>
		<intro>MMBase 1.6.5 is released, shortly after the 1.6.4 release. This is because MMBase-1.6.4 contains a wrong class wich may result in rather confusing output of some queries. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="17397" owner="admin">
		<body>Kennisnet,the Dutch internet organisation for primary, secondary and professional education in the Netherlands, announced today, September 3, that it’s future web development will be based on the Open Source Content Management System MMBase.

Kennisnet provides thousands of schools with their portals to effectively communicate with students, teachers and schools. Earlier this year Kennisnet has year already decided substantiate it’s commitment to 
Open Source and MMBase by participating in the MMBase Foundation. 
Kennisnet has made the strategic commitment to further develop it’s application using Open Source software and where possible to return it’s developments to the wider community under Open Source license. 

Michiel Westerman (managing director Kennisnet) stated that “we view it as our responsibility to use public money in the best and most efficient manner. Open Source development of our applications for education 
purposes best enable this goal”.

Together with the other major partners, like the municipality of Amsterdam, broadcasters (VPRO, EO, TeleacNOT, Publieke Omroep), other educational institutions (Surf, ROCvA) and many others, this will 
give a new boost to innovative development. The MMBase Foundation is very pleased to welcome Kennisnet to the MMBase family. Kennisnet has today deployed a revised homepage (not MMBase) and several new portals. All of which meet international standards on accessibility. 

The first sites Kennisnet deployed with MMBase are:
http://web.kennisnet2.nl/po/ict/
http://web.kennisnet2.nl/vo/ict/
http://web.kennisnet2.nl/bve/ict/
http://web.kennisnet2.nl/bve/groen/ict/
http://web.kennisnet2.nl/vo/scholier_vmbo/
The other portals will follow in due course.

For further information, please also read the Kennisnet pressrelease (Dutch only) or visit the international section of Kennisnet for more information:  
http://www.kennisnet.nl/portal/overkennisnet/internationalvisitors/aboutkennisnet/ </body>
		<title>Kennisnet deploys first MMBase sites, more to come</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Kennisnet chooses MMBase for future web development.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="18515" owner="admin">
		<body>In this weeks meeting in Brussels the European Parliament will make a decision on the regulations concerning (software) patents. The MMBase Foundation argued strongly against any regulations on the use of software, other than acknowledging the -now used- copyrights. Over 250.000 Europeans signed a petition against the proposed regulations. In the Netherlands the issue wrongfully never made to the front page, although liberal democrats held a firm pledge last week in favour of open standards and open source.
Open source sure isn’t the only development that will suffer from any patents, but for sure it will suffer the most. OSS-communities never claimed any inventions: they want to share them with the whole world. The effect on Open Standards will even be harsher, everyone will try and claim any standard that is widely used.

Let's hope all European MP's read what Objectweb.org stated on their website: &quot;Warning against software patents! Software patents are a serious matter - and we lived decades without them. We warn  the European Parliament that no decision should be taken in a hurry or under the pressure of some lobbies. Better think twice before taking the risk of undermining our whole software industry.&quot;
</body>
		<title>Appeal from MMBase to European MPs: say NO to patents</title>
		<subtitle>Patents on software will have great negative impact on innovation</subtitle>
		<intro>We have made a last appeal on all Dutch MPs  to say no to software patents. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="20115" owner="admin">
		<body>The capital of the Dutch Province Friesland, Leeuwarden, has chosen MMBase to build their new corporate websites. Leeuwarden is the second city to do so, Amsterdam already started using this Open Source web content management system in 2001.

Leeuwarden made a choice for MMBase, because robust CMS features are combined with multi channel communication. The northern Dutch city hopes that the new website will combine an enhanced maintenance environment with more interactivity. In the future the functionality of the site will grow to a transaction oriented environment. Deployment of the site (www.leeuwarden.nl) is planned in January 2004. The other open source products used by Leeuwarden for their new dynamic web environment are Linux, Tomcat and MySQL. The cities of Amsterdam and Leeuwarden will work together with The MMBase Foundation on future development. MMBase partner Finalist IT Group and The Missing Link Company are, respectively, responsible for the implementation and design. 
</body>
		<title>Leeuwarden chooses MMBase</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Leeuwarden, the capital of the Dutch province Friesland, has chosen MMBase for their new corporate websites. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="20122" owner="admin">
		<body>On the 5th of November 2003 the seminar &quot;E-learning; the evolution in learning&quot; took place. More than 80 visitors attended the Event, and&amp;nbsp;were engaged in an interactive program on e-learning. They learned about what Didactor can do for organizations, and how it can be used.

The opening of the day was done by Jo Lahaye, the CEO of the MMBase Foundation. He started with a short explanation of the Dutch Open Source Content Management initiative MMBase. More and more organizations use MMBase successfully. Didactor was build with MMBase. The first presenter of the day was Arko van Brakel, partner of The Mediator Group. The appearance of interactive media is the next revolution after the industrial revolution, according to Van Brakel. Knowledge and information still play an important role in our society. The youth of 2003, the Nintendo generation, are handling information very differently from adults. They are used to working with computers and use them in all aspects of their lives. Because of that, within the educational field, more and more use is made of Internet technology. The use of electronic learning in education and business is therefore an irreversible process. The next speaker was Jolanda van Goor, an E-learning consultant. She discussed the characteristics of E-learning, like the student centered approach, and cooperative learning. She also explained the conditions for successful use of E-learning. She mentioned things like broadly based acceptance within an organization, the quality of the teaching material, and the possibility of blended learning. She closed her presentation by demonstrating the Didactor Software (for a demo, go to www.didactor.nl and click on demo). 

After that there were a number of real live showcases of institutions that work with Didactor. Richard Post of the Evangelische Omroep (EO) presented the history of deployment of their online course ‘Wa@rom Jezus’ (Why Jezus). After experimenting with different systems, they have now successfully implemented Didactor. The course is offered as a blended concept. The course is supported by a so called ‘e-coach’, who assists the students when they have questions. With this E-learning environment the EO can reach target markets that are otherwise hard to reach. After every course the results are evaluated intensively. The conclusion for the EO is that E-learning makes an important contribution towards realizing their goals. 

The last presentation of the day was by Heleen Riper of the Trimbos Instituut. The Trimbos Instituut is applying E-learning to renew ways to provide care. At this point they are working on a Didactor course for depressed elderly. By ways of an online course the elderly are able to work towards improving their situation anonymously. The course will be tested soon, at the Kenniswijk in Eindhoven. After a summarization of the chairman, the meeting ended and while enjoying drinks and snacks, there where still long talks about Didactor and it’s possibilities to improve the educational program.</body>
		<title>Didactor seminar: the evolution in E-learning</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>On the 5th of November 2003 the seminar &quot;E-learning; the evolution in learning&quot; was held at a wonderfull location at&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;TU-Delft. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="21070" owner="default">
		<body>In the OSOSS newsletter Jo Lahaye, the CEO of the MMBase Foundation, wrote in his column that OSOSS would soon enrich the MMBase community with a tool to quickly create and add tables and lists in MMBase. This moment has arrived and the so-called DataMatrix, developed in collaboration, by OSOSS order, has been given to the MMBase community.

The thought behind the donation is simple; join the principle of open source software. You solve a question or problem with software, you share the solution with the rest of the world and invite people to think along with you, and continue development together.

For the development of the website www.ososs.nl, OSOSS used the content management system MMBase. OSOSS wanted to use tables for the creation of conveniently arranged lists of open source products, open source distributors en open standards. They joint forces with two other programs of the Foundation ICTU, namely ELO and Advies Overheid.nl, and bundled development wishes, money, and knowledge. Together with Hartman Communication BV (for communication in computerization) and the technical Internet company Q42 (focused on the design and the construction of user-friendly interfaces and Internet applications) the DataMatrix was build. By donating the DataMatrix to the MMBase community, the tool can be used by everybody to create dataoverviews, and of course the development can be continued by other parties. For examples of the application, please visit the OSOSS website www.ososs.nl. 

The DataMatrix can be downloaded from the MMBase website, in the section ‘packages’. You will also find an installation and user manual. </body>
		<title>OSOSS donates the DataMatrix to the Foundation</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The application can be downloaded from this website. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="21843" owner="default">
		<body>Source: Emerce http://www.emerce.nl/archives/nieuws/Media_Marketing/15495.html 

On December 30 IKON starts a TV program on mobile communication and Internet, targeting teenagers.  The program has been labled R U Tlkng 2 Me (Are you talking to me) and is already available online on a site developed in cooperation with Kenniswijk (Eindhoven, www.kenniswijk.nl). 

The Dutch Interdenominational Broadcaster (IKON) says it is happy to be working with Kenniswijk. &quot;We did not have a sufficient funds to set up a site and therefore worked together with Kenniswijk, who was looking for a project around children and mobile communication&quot;, says the spokeswoman of the IKON. &quot;Because of this, we were able to add an extensive site to our program&quot;.

The site was built by Finalist IT Group and offers additional information on the program. It also offers several tools, for example for creating ring tones which will be 75 percent cheaper than an average ring tone, according to the initiator www.rutlkng2me.nl. There is also an online portrait album, to which pictures can be sent through SMS, and can be edited with an additional application. According to Finalist this application &quot;has never been used before&quot;. The application is developed in the open source CMS MMBase. One of the advantages is that it is possible to send a MMS-picture regardless of the telecom provider used. 

The complete program is already available online, and can be watched with Windows Media, Realmedia of via First Mile TV. The individual programs are 15 minutes each. &quot;With this we try to anticipate on a situation in which people decide what they want to see, at what time. Something that will happen when everybody uses broadband&quot;, says to the IKON spokeswoman.  

The programs will be broadcasted weekly through Z@ppelin. Themes that will come up for discussion are chatting, sending SMS-messages, phone-etiquette, games and the cost of calling mobile. &quot;The reason for making such a program is that we want to make programs for and by young people, and digital communication plays a large role in their lives&quot;, says the spokeswoman.  

An additional advantage is that parents and others in the surroundings of children and teenagers also get an insight into the way they communicate digitally.  With that comes the risk that it will be mostly parents that will be watching TV. &quot;That probably won't be a problem&quot;, says the spokeswoman. &quot;For teenagers everything that has to do with mobile telephony is interesting, those phones are 'hot'. Besides, they also get practical information on how they can prevent their bills from getting too high. We also show how Dutch celebrities use their mobile phone and the Internet, what 'Goede Tijden, Slechte Tijden' (a popular soap program) actresses have to say about that, appeals to them&quot;.</body>
		<title>IKON's youth TV program online with MMBase.</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The program on mobile and Internet has been labled R U Tlkng 2 Me (Are you talking to me) and is already available online.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="21878" owner="default">
		<body>Thursday the 8th of January we organize a Bug Fixing day to fix some bugs that should be solved before the official MMBase 1.7 release. Developers that want to join the bug fixing team can join IRC to help us (server irc.slashnet.org, at channel #mmbase). We will be there till 17:30 to fix MMBase bugs.

After a hard day working we will have diner at the VPRO and end the evening with a 'developers meeting' and a drink. Developers that want to attend the developers meeting and the dinner, please let us know by sending an email to info@mmbase.org. 

</body>
		<title>Bug Fixing Day</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>To ensure a stable and bug free MMBase 1.7 release we organise a MMBase bug fixing day the 8th of January.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="22491" owner="default">
		<body>In 2003 the Mediator Group introduced Didactor (www.didactor.nl), an e-learning environment based on MMBase. Didactor has been successfully implemented at, among others, the Trimbos Institute, the EO, and Residentie.net, a portal for citizens in The Hague. This January, release 1.4 will be available, with improvement on the usability of the application. Release 2.0, later this year, will include new functionalities, like a portfolio manager.

The main adjustments to 1.4 are related to the editor. The new editor uses a different interface and works more user-friendly. 

Release 2.0 will contain new functionalities. These are: an import function, a portfolio manager and an intake and evaluation module. The import function is used for importing external courseware. Using this importer will ensure good exchange of courseware between different e-learning environments. The portfolio manager extends the possibilities for students to control their learning space. This version also offers many new options for storing personal information and displaying work to others. And, last but not least, the release will have an intake and evaluation module. 

These new tools support an efficient learning process, and a student centered approach. At Residentie.net, for example Didactor learns users how the portal works, so that it can be used to its full potential. The Trimbos Instituut is applying Didactor to renew ways to provide care. Evangelische Omroep (EO) uses Didactor for their online course ‘Wa@rom Jezus’ (Why Jezus). After experimenting with different systems, they have now successfully implemented Didactor. The ‘Wa@rom Jezus’ course is offered as a blended concept and is supported by a so called ‘e-coach’, who assists the students when they have questions. 

For more information on Didactor, please contact Joost Becking;  joost@mediatorgroup.com</body>
		<title>New releases of Didactor in 2004</title>
		<subtitle>The new tools support an efficient learning process, and a student centered approach.</subtitle>
		<intro>This January, release 1.4 will be available.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="22904" owner="default">
		<body>Information about changes between MMBase-1.6.x and MMBase-1.7.0 is included in the releasenotes (though it's not complete yet).

This rc can be used to test the next release. Please help us by testing it and send your test results to the mmbase developers mailinglist. If you find bugs, please report them in the bugtracker.

</body>
		<title>MMBase-1.7.0 Release Candidate 1</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The first release candidate of the next major MMBase release is available. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="23106" owner="default">
		<body>January 28 2004, Oude Meer – 

This week, The Mediator Group (TMG) received the quality indicator ‘ICT- bedrijf voor het onderwijs’. TMG develops and implements the e-learning application Didactor. Didactor is based on the, in the Netherlands widely used, web content management system (CMS) MMBase. With Didactor, TMG shows that MMBase lends itself sucessfully for the development of a wide variety of webbased applications. Didactor will later this year be released as open source software (Mozilla license, like MMBase itself).
 
The issueing of this quality indication is a shared initiative of the Foundation’ ICT op school’ (ICT at school) and ‘Nederland ICT’ (The Netherlands ICT).
 
The quality mark is developed for ICT companies and schools in the primary and secondary education. The goal of the quality mark is the improvement of ICT applications in the educational field. ICT companies that want to qualify for this quality mark have to live up to certain quality standards. These contain things like: the quality system, complaint handling, knowledge and insight into the educational field and the professionalism of the company. 
 
With an electronic e-learning environment, Didactor enables educational institutions to integrate electronic learning into the education program. Because the product is developed with the open source software MMBase, users don’t have the pay a licence fee for the use of Didactor. 
 
The quality mark shows that Didactor can stand all comparison with competitors, in both a technical and didactical way.
 
The website www.kwaliteitsregeling.nl shows a register with all organisation that have received the quality mark.

More information : www.mediatorgroup.com/, www.didactor.nl, www.mmbase.org, www.ictopschool.net/ en www.nederlandict.nl/

Editorial note:

Additonal information on the Mediator Group:

The Mediator Group
Contact:			Raymond van Ham
Postion:			Marketing &amp; Sales manager
Telephone:		+ 31 (0)20 682 18 02 
E-mail: 			raymond@mediatorgroup.com
</body>
		<title>Press Release Didactor</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The supplier of the MMBase E-learning application receives the quality indicator ‘ICT-bedrijf voor het onderwijs’ (‘ICT company for the educational field’). </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="23796" owner="default">
		<body>New with this release are the applications that are not part of the distro: Cloudcontextsecurity, media, email and scan. These can also be downloaded from the above location.

For Postgresql users there's a special notice in the releasenotes.

This rc can be used to test the next major release of MMBase. The best way to test it is to do a clean install, install applications, test all examples, test the different type of editors (jsp-editors, my_editors, wizards) and let us know your experiences.

We also need upgrade tests: upgrade a (test) system from MMBase-1.6.x to this rc and let us know if you encountered any problems.</body>
		<title>MMBase-1.7.0 Release Candidate 2</title>
		<subtitle>The second release candidate of the next major MMBase release is available.</subtitle>
		<intro>There are a lot of bugs fixed between the rc1 and the rc2 release and pdf version of most documentation is included.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="24154" owner="default">
		<body>During the introduction of the evening Rob Vermeulen announced that the upcomming developers meeting will be held the 6th of May 2004. Put this day already in your agenda :-). A proposal of MMC elections which was promised by the MMC during the first developers meeting of this year, was sent to the developers mailing list. In april, two MMC members will resign to make place for new candidates.

Henk Hangyi showed how the current MMBase documentation is structured, and announced that the Documentation project will be closed when the MMBase 1.7 release will be official. 

Michiel Meeuwissen showed that the taglib set has been growing from 444 to 745 features, and that over 60 bugs have been fixed in the new taglib set. The new taglib set (1.7) contains a lot of new, nice features and Michiel showed some of them. See the attached url for Michiel's presenation and the new taglib features.

Daniel ockeloen talked about the application 2 project. Daniel showed how the package manager is working, and that still a lot has to be made. He also announce that he will make the package manager availabe 2 weeks after the offical release of MMBase 1.7. A link to his presenation is attached to this article.

Jo Lahaye informed the developers about the role of the foundation. 

Gerard van Enk started a discussion about the new MMBase 1.8 release. Which projects do we want to fulfill for this release. The discussion became a bit more generic, and we discussed about the need of a roadmap (Vision). The idea is to start a RoadMap project in the near future.</body>
		<title>Developers Meeting March 2004</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The last developers meeting, hosted by Finalist, gave a good idea of some recent MMBase topics.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="24247" owner="default">
		<body>&lt;P&gt;The Dutch city Hilversum, home of most Dutch broadcasters and many other multi media organisations, recently decided to build its new website with the open source web content management system MMBase. In basic, Hilversum will use the Amsterdam-style MMBase-implementation named &quot;Web In A Box&quot;. The site will be deployed in Spring 2004. Hilversum is the third Dutch city to use MMBase for their corporate site (following Amsterdam and Leeuwarden). MMBase is used by many other cities, but for non-corporate sites, like e.g. Residentie.net in The Hague.&lt;/P&gt;</body>
		<title>Hilversum chooses MMBase</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Dutch &quot;media city&quot; moves to MMBase.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="24367" owner="default">
		<body>
The national computer network for higher education and research in the Netherlands, SURFnet, is going to use the open source content management system MMBase for it's corporate website, as well as several other (thematic) portal sites.

SURFnet connects the networks of universities, colleges, research centres, academic hospitals and scientific libraries to one another and to other networks in Europe and the rest of the world. SURFnet is part of the world wide Internet. The SURFnet network enables its users to communicate with other network users and to consult the Internet from their office or their home PC. SURFnet provides rapid and reliable connections to educational institutions and research centres abroad using advanced technologies and high-quality infrastructure. 

The Dutch internet organisation for primary, secondary and professional education in the Netherlands, Kennisnet, is already using MMBase. The two organisations are already working together and will stimulate more collaboration.

The SURFnet application will be implemented by Finalist IT Group and Q42. Deployment is planned in the summer of 2004. The SURFnet application will be based upon the sites that were developed for the city of Leeuwarden and Kennisnet.
</body>
		<title>Surfnet renews portals</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>SURFnet announced today, it will use MMBase for future development of it's webportals. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="25003" owner="default">
		<body>This is the first release in which a lot of functionality has been
seperated from the core and put into applications. This process will
continue after this release. The core will become smaller and MMBase wil
become more modular.
 
Other highlights are:
 
- completely rewritten storage layer
- new query framework
- media application
- a lot of new taglib features (see documentation for more info)</body>
		<title>MMBase-1.7.0 final release available</title>
		<subtitle>The next major MMBase release is available.</subtitle>
		<intro>The MMBase developers team is proud to present the long awaited final Release of MMBase-1.7.0 (only a few days after MMBase, as an open source project, turned 4, 3 april).</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="25045" owner="default">
		<body>The struggle against software patent is coming into the next phase. European Parliament last year voted against software patents 'as such' and accepted many amendements in that direction. At this moment the commission is working on a new regulation that will be proposed soon. Most people expect it to be more or less a copy of the first version. And there is doubt whether the Parliament will stand up against the commission once more. For that reason a lot of organisations are organising a new protest in Brussels next wednesday (April 14). We ask you all to support this protest against these harmfull ideas. Please see ffii.org for more information.

The CEO of the MMBase Foundation wrote an opinion for the Dutch Automatiseringsgids (Dutch only):

Een Amerikaans bedrijf claimt patent te hebben op het aanbieden van streaming audio en video vanaf een webserver.Anderen, zoals Amazon, hebben nagenoeg alle routines voor het doen van aankopen op internet gepatenteerd; kijk bijvoorbeeld eens op http://webshop.ffii.org. En ook technieken die zorgen voor “filtering” van elektronische berichten, de zogenaamde spam-filters, zijn geoctrooieerd. Wie denkt dat dit een grap is, moet ik teleurstellen. Het is slechts een hele kleine greep uit de vele tienduizenden “softwarepatenten” die door octrooibureaus in de VS en Europa zijn toegekend. 

In de loop van vorig jaar is door de Europese Commissie een voorstel geformuleerd om tot een  Europese richtlijn te komen. Nu heeft ieder EU-land zijn eigen regels. In dat voorstel werd de octrooieerbaarheid van software als uitgangspunt genomen. De afgelopen jaren heeft het Europees octrooibureau (EOB) in München daar vast een voorschot opgenomen door tegen de letter en geest van wetten in, meer dan 30.000 (!!) patenten toe te kennen aan wat de wet noemt &quot;programma's voor computers&quot; en wat het Europees Patentburo &quot;computer-geïmplementeerde uitvindingen&quot; is gaan noemen.

Eind vorig jaar liet het Europees Parlement middels tientallen amandementen weinig heel van het voorstel, waardoor nu gewerkt wordt aan een nieuwe versie. Echter, naar verluidt wordt nog steeds als uitgangspunt gehanteerd dat het patenteren van software een goede zaak is. 

Vreemd genoeg is voornamelijk vanuit de open source gemeenschappen fel geprotesteerd tegen het uitgangspunt dat algemene software patenteerbaar kan zijn, terwijl de grotere Nederlandse softwarebedrijven zich muisstil houden. Van een weloverwogen eigenbelang kan daarbij geen sprake zijn, want zij bezitten namelijk geen, of nauwelijks, patenten. Wellicht dat angst voor beschadiging van de goede relaties met Amerikaanse branchegenoten een rol speelt. 

Behalve Cap Gemini Ernst en Young (CGE&amp;Y) die vorige jaar in de NRC aangaven grote problemen te verwachten door software-octrooien, heeft geen van de belangrijke spelers op de Nederlandse markt blijkbaar door wat ze te wachten staat. Ook al verdienen zij hun geld voornamelijk met beheer en services, ze leveren allen ook maatwerk-oplossingen. En iedereen die straks software-code schrijft die inbreuk maakt op een gepatenteerde routine, hangt mogelijk een forse schadeclaim boven het hoofd. Juridische processen in de VS laten zien dat het hierbij inmiddels om ‘echt’ geld gaat. Zo belsoot Microsoft Paasweekend om InterTrust 440 miljoen dollar te betalen in een octrooizaak. In het betoog van CGE&amp;Y eind vorig jaar werd er terecht op gewezen dat toetsing op een patent-inbreuk “vooraf”, zeer specialistisch en dus kostbaar werk is. Tevens werd gesteld dat een patentwerking van 20 jaar ongepast is in een wereld waar 3 jaar al een eeuwigheid lijkt. 

Wellicht dat door het verzet vanuit de open source gemeenschappen, die geheel in de wetenschappelijke traditie juist willen bevorderen dat op al ontwikkelde kennis wordt voortgebouwd,  aanbieders van gesloten software denken dat zij niet zo snel inbreuk maken op patenten. Tenslotte is de broncode niet open. Dit is evenwel een misvatting. Het gaat namelijk niet om schending van het auteursrecht, maar om schending van een routine, inbreuk op een gepatenteerd “concept”. En dat is precies wat er niet deugt aan software-octrooien. In verschillende, notabene Amerikaanse, onderzoeken is dit inmiddels aangetoond, maar de conclusie is (nog) niet dat het patenteren van software-routines wellicht beter achterwege had kunnen blijven. 

Nogal wat organisaties menen dat ze moeten pleiten voor softwarepatenten om hun producten te beschermen. Naar mijn stellige overtuiging zijn de meeste producten echter afdoende beschermd binnen de bestaande regelgeving, met bijvoorbeeld merkenrecht, auteursrecht en het huidige patentrecht. Tenslotte kan software -in termen van regeltjes code- heel eenvoudig worden beschermd door de broncode gesloten te houden. En veel software is bedoeld om uitsluitend in één specifiek product te functioneren; ook daar is afscherming eenvoudig te regelen. De brief van o.a. Philips aan onze regering waarin gepleit wordt vóór patenteerbaarheid van software, doet vermoeden dat dit onderscheid niet is gemaakt. 

Software dient vrij te blijven van patenten. Al was het maar omdat “we” beginnen met een achterstand op de Amerikaanse softwareindustrie die we nooit meer inlopen. Tenslotte was (en is) het patenteren van software in veel Europese landen niet mogelijk, of heel moeilijk. Het protest is massaal (http://petition.eurolinux.org) en vele vooraanstaande wetenschappers betogen dat softwarepatenten innovatie belemmeren en de economie vertragen. Bovendien zal de achterstand van Europa op de VS toenemen. Het ICT-handelstekort van de EU met de VS bedraagt nu een slordige 35 miljard dollar per jaar. Dit zal substantieel stijgen als software octrooieerbaar wordt. Naar verwachting zal in mei 2004 een nieuw plan worden ingediend dat op belangrijke onderdelen vergelijkbaar is met het vorige. Laten we hopen dat het Europees Parlement andermaal de rug recht weet te houden. Liever geen regeling, dan een hele slechte. 

Jo Lahaye
directeur Stichting MMBase
april 2004
</body>
		<title>Software patents threaten Europe</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>April 14: protest in Brussels. Statement from MMBase.  </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="27066" owner="default">
		<body>(For more information, and the presentations held on the Event, please go to the Foundation site (www.mmbase.org/foundation) and look for MMEvent in the navigation). 

The MMBase community of users, developers, and implementators, and interested companies that visited the Event, did not only see how MMBase is currently used within governmental and educational institutes and businesses. Also a number of prominent companies like Philips Medical Systems shared their experiences with the use of open source and MMBase and the related policy questions. 

There were also end users, talking about the features and advantages of their MMBase applications. An enthusiastic end user like Wim de Bie proudly showed his Bieslog, a multimedia site with more than 200.000 unique visitors a month, on which he publishes at least three times a day. The website features text, film, video, sound and pictures. 

Ruben van Wendel de Joode, researcher at the Technische Universiteit Delft opened the MMEvent4. The TU Delft is going to invest in open source research in the next few years and wants to work together with the MMBase community. Van Wendel de Joode studies open source communities and is enthusiastic about the Dutch open source developments and specifically about MMBase, with its CMS widely used within the public sector. 

Marc Bressers is program manager of OSOSS (Open Standards en Open Source Software for the government), a platform for open source knowledge exchange. OSOSS works together with the MMBase community. MMBase is already used by many governmental institutions and many more are taking the use of MMBase into consideration, explains Bressers.

According to Bressers some policy makers in governmental and educational institutions and companies are still prejudice against open source software. The general idea is that Open source software has an idealistic approach and that the software is not suitable for (semi-)commercial use. Changing this view is one of the major tasks of the OSOSS, which programmes inform governmental institutions about the use and development of open source applications

Governmental institutions that use open source are, according to Bressers, generally positive and try to increase their participation in this field. The government policy on open source and ICT (as put forwared in the ‘Vendrik resolution’) has targeted to decreasing supplier dependency. Reasons for government institutions to use open source are diverse, varying from bad experiences with closed source software (vendor lock-ins) to the need for shared development. 

Some institutions have unrealistically high expectations of open source software. Through consultancy, OSOSS aims for strong embedded open source standards, like CANOS (Nederlandse Catalogus van Open Standaarden).

OSOSS: http://www.ososs.nl

Joost van Stiphout, of the Electronic Municipality (EGEM), advises municipalities on ICT issues. EGEM notices a strong increasing interest in open source software amongst its members. One of the main risks of closed source software, when used by municipalities, is the loss of control over the use of information about its citizens.

EGEM has constructed a project site for Dutch municipalities based on MMBase. This site makes it possible for municipalities to work together on projects; documents can be exchanged and forums maintained. The project site application will be offered to the MMBase community. 
 
EGEM: http://www.egem.nl. 
 
Fred de Vries, Open University the Netherlands (OUNL), points out the general state of affairs regarding electronic learning systems. According to his findings, educational needs concerning e-learning applications are generally developed and well defined only after the purchase of software. Educational needs should define the choice for a system, not the other way around, he says. 
 
The Open University researches open source electronic learning systems, under the authority of the Digital University in The Netherlands. The outcome of this research will be published in the course of this summer. MMBase’s e-learning system Didactor will also be taken along.
 
The motive for conducting this research lies in the discussion about open content and intellectual property. In the Netherland and abroad, many educational institutes, forsee major problems concerning these issues (more information on the subject of open content and intellectual property can be found on: http://www.sakaiproject.org/ ). De Vries stresses the importance of increasing awareness of platform independency and the use of learning technological specifications like IMS and QTI.
 
Nederlands Normalisatie Instituut: http://www.nen.nl/nl/act/spec/leertech
Surf Six expertisegrope: http://e-learning.surf.nl/six
Digitale Universiteit: http://www.digiuni.nl
Open Universiteit: http://www.ounl.nl
 
Theo Wittering, Ordina, stresses that open source software offers users more transparency. Users of OS software have more influence on the process of development and innovation of their product. The development of open source systems is demand-oriented and easy to access. 
 
An example is Didactor, an electronic learning method, partly based on the MMBase engine. Didactor is developed by the EO, The Mediatorgroup, Finalist IT Group and is presently used by Den Haag and Amsterdam. 
 
The Mediator Group: http://www.mediatorgroup.com
Didactor: http://www.didactor.nl
 
Andres Steijaert is project leader at SURFnet, a co-operation between Dutch master and bachelor educational institutes. SURFnet comprises 150 organisations and about 750.000 users. After a thorough study of content management systems, SURFnet chose MMBase for their web development. They have built a new MMBase application, based on previous developments by the municipality of Leeuwarden en Kennisnet. Next to features like information management using a browser, workflow, version control, separation of layout and content, scheduling of messages, and content labelling (classification), the SURFnet CMS offers a real-time response forum, and a tool to define tailor made URL’s.
 
The reason for Surfnet’s choice for MMBase lies in the strong MMBase community. The SURFnet build application will soon be open source available. 
 
Surfnet: http://www.surfnet.nl
 
Frank van der Linden, Philips Medical Systems, notices a strong increase in the use of open source and the so called bounded community systems within Philip since 2003.
 
Some of these open source systems are known to their clients, which in itself could be a reason to implement the open source product in Philips electronics. Philips’s clients generally rate the use of open source products as positive. Another reason to use open source is that it that users do not need to pay for licence fees, unlike closed source. A third important reason for Philips to use open source is the prohibition of the use of certain closed source software by governments like China . 
 
Questions concerning the use of open source software in respect to their own patents and also problems regarding liability in case of damage are aspects still discussed within Philips. After a corporate policy has been defined, Van der Linden expects the use of open source software within Philips to increase. 

Dick Rijken, chairman of the MMBase Foundation, wants to stimulate users of MMBase to give more feedback. He explains that, thanks to the Publieke Omroep, there is new and improved MMBase documentation. Release 1.7 is the first release within the new approach of making the MMBase core lighter. Important issues for the future of MMBase are, according to him:
- The relation between modules/ components and the MMBase core. 
- Limiting the scope: what is MMBase and what not, and how to deal with this?
 
MMBase: http://www.mmbase.org
 
Pierre van Rooden, member of the MMBase Management Committee sees a number of tasks for the MMC (MMBase Management Committee): 
- keeping together the community of developers. 
- carrying out the opinions of the community of developers
- developing a long term vision
 
At this moment, MMBase is supported by 16 committers and a group of active developers. Van Rooden requests all participants of the Event to bring their developers in contact with the MMBase community of developers. 
MMBase: http://www.mmbase.org
 
Henk Hangyi, CEO of MMatch, opens the session of MMBase showcases. Hangyi announces a number of new developments: statistics, e-mails in HTML-format, imagemaps, etc. He explains the strategie on these development. The community is also working on a peer-to-peer network for the MMBase packages. This way, all the MMBase packages and modules placed on different servers will be available and downloadable from the MMBase site, and therefore easier to find. 
 
Bruno Felix, Submarine, developed a forum for ‘web in de wijk’ in co-operation with Kennisnet. This forum offers citizens an easy way to make their own webpages and publish them on the Internet. 
 
Web in de Wijk: http://www.webindewijk.nl
Submarine: http://www.submarine.nl
 
PARALLELSESSION I: scientific workshop 

Margot Wijnen (Innovatieplatform), gives a short introduction at the scientific workshop. The Innovation Platform invites the MMBase community to write a report about the intended European legislation on software patents. What are the obstacles to software development and innovations according to the MMBase community?
 
Daniel Ockeloen (MMBase developer), talks about the challenges that the MMBase community is facing. For example, how to get synergy from co-operation? Not the architecture of the software, but the architecture of the community is decisive, according to Ockeloen. The developers community is working to decrease and lighten the core of MMBase. The consequences according to Ockeloen are that the area around the core (the applications and packages) will become a 'gray' area. Ockeloen prefers to see MMBase develop towards an end product. 
 
Frank van der Linden (Philips medical systems), stresses that not all companies want to offer their components open source. Making software open source also means offering support and maintenance. Van der Linden explains the ideas of Philips on the open source way (consolidation) vs. the formal way (pre-deployment definion) and the consequences both options have for an organisation.
 
Ángel Vaca (direction of Fundecyt, Extremadura, Spain). The province of Extremadura sees the stimulation of the use of information technology as the key to successful economic development of the Extremadura region, one of the poorest areas in Europe. With their project LinEx, the government has succeeded in providing access to a computer for more that 50% of the population. Extremadura developed user friendly Linux-based software called LinEx, that is now distributed to all the computers in Extremadura. 
 
Ángel Vaca is also connected to ETHOS, the European Trust Platform for Homogenizing Open Source Software Efforts. ETHOS strives for the explanation of the rules for the production of components and the definitions of quality standards in the Free Open Source Industrie (FLOSS).
 
Gnulinex: http://www.gnulinex.org
 
Wim de Bie (famous Dutch TV personality, VPRO) is the general editor of a weblog for the broadcasting institution VPRO. He is an enthusiastic MMBase user, and publishes at least three times a day on his weblog called Bieslog. His multimedia Bieslog is developed with MMBase and contains many features, like an extensive archive on the site. De Bie also has plans for live broadcasting on his Bieslog. With more that 200.000 unique visitors per month, he has a very successful site. Within a room full of smiling people, he managed to share his excitement and make this presentation a pleasant closure of a successful and innovative MMBase day. 
 
Bieslog: http://bieslog.vpro.nl
 
For more information, please contact the Foundation, jo@mmbase.org , 035 6288088.
</body>
		<title>Successful fourth Event</title>
		<subtitle>Hundred people visited fourth annual Event.</subtitle>
		<intro>On june 9, some 100 attendees enjoyed a day full of presentations and debate at the TU Delft.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="27320" owner="default">
		<body>In recent months, we've seen several open source releases of MMBase-related functionality.For example a webshop, mailform, email application, linkchecker, and other packages. At this moment several other people and organizations are working on the open source release of a project tool, an MMBase-interface to the widely used authentication tool (www.a-select.org), a forum application, an e-learning environment, etc. In time they can all be found on this site (see: download -&gt; packages).

And today, June 29 in the year 2004, we announce with great pleasure, that the Java IRC Server (Jircs), developed under supervision of the Dutch public broadcasting organization EO by Jaco de Groot and Jelle Katsman has been made open source. 

In the summer of 2002 the EO was looking for a chat server that could communicate with Flash (Macromedia) and their content management system MMBase (www.mmbase.org). The technical team decided not to invent a new chat protocol, but to create a chat server in  Java, based on the IRC protocol. There are two interfaces available to configure Jircs as a normal IRC server and as a chat server that communicates with flash clients (developed by Jelle Katsman) and checks with MMBase for users and channels; so people logged in to the website are automatically logged in to the IRC server. Your own design can easily be integrated with the flash client. 

In several audio's with Fokke Kooistra (CTO of the EO) and also with the MMBase Foundation, everyone involved came to the conclusion that an open source release of this chat would be greatly appreciated by the MMBase community. And hopefully many others!  Because Jircs can also be used independent from MMBase, as you can create your own repository. 

Jircs has been proven stable and has many advanced features. In the coming period Jircs will be maintained by Jaco de Groot (www.dynasol.nl) and Jelle Katsman (flash client), with support from the MMBase Foundation. In the near future Jircs can be found on Jircs.org. 
The release is now available on: http://www.dynasol.nl/jircs/
The zip-files also contain all documentation necessary.

In the past few months Jaco de Groot and Jelle Katsman worked very hard to make this release possible. Putting sources on a website is one thing. Writing adequate documentation regarding requirements, installation and functionality another. 

We therefore all owe many thanks to:
Jaco de Groot, http://www.dynasol.nl, Jaco@dynasol.nl (maintainer irc server)
Jelle Katsman, Jircs@katsman.nl (maintainer flash client)
Fokke Kooistra, http://www.eo.nl (fokke.kooistra@eo.nl). 

(Flash is a registered trademark from Macromedia.)

June 28,
MMBase Foundation.
</body>
		<title>Chat Jircs now open source.</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Java IRC Server (Jircs), developed under supervision of the Dutch public broadcasting organization EO, by Jaco de Groot and Jelle Katsman.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="27360" owner="default">
		<body>The Dutch minister of Economic Affairs, Brinkhorst, has to recall his support for the EU software patent directive. Dutch parliament on July 1 forced the government to change the positive vote into an abstention. 

As far as we know it is the first time in EU history a country withdraws a given vote in the European council of ministers. The MMBase Foundation, other open source communities, SME's, scientists and economists fiercely opposed the Directive on Software Patents, arguing that it destroys innovation and will lead to never ending legal issues. 

We hope of course that this signal will also inspire other European governments to rethink their support for the directive. As we argued before, it is not in the interest of European ICT industry.

After the directive is translated into all EU-languages, a formal vote on the issue will take place; at this moment the given support is considered to be only a 'political agreement'. After that, European parliament will have a second chance to vote against the directive. Because it's the second time the issue is debated, only a 2/3 majority can actually sent the directive to the waste basket. This European democracy regulation could well be a great hindrance in prohibiting this directive from going into effect unchanged.</body>
		<title>Support for Softwarepatents recalled</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>On July 1, parliament forced Dutch government to withdraw its support for the EU directive on software patents.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="31562" owner="admin">
		<body>There are a lot of bugs fixed in this release, see releasenotes.txt for more information about the bugs that are fixed.

Because of the amount of bugs that have been fixed since the previous release, you are advised to upgrade your existing installations. Please refer to the 
upgrade.txt file for information.</body>
		<title>MMBase-1.7.1 final release available</title>
		<subtitle>The first bugfix release for MMBase-1.7 is available.</subtitle>
		<intro>The MMBase developers team is proud to present the first bugfix release of MMBase-1.7.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="32564" owner="admin">
		<body>This mailing list will be a Dutch mailing list which is meant for organizations that use MMBase, for organizations that develop MMBase, and for everybody that wants to be on the list. Examples for which the new mailing list can be used are:
- Inform the community about new packages (applications), or new versions of packages.
- Discussions about how to donate packages to the MMBase community, and how to make packages open source.
- Inform yourself if functionality already exists. If not, you can ask organizations to collaborate.
- Sharing experiences with the community.

The MMC only wants to facilitate the community with a tool to be able to community easily. The community itself will probably come up with more interesting topics to discuss on this new mailing list. An overview of actual MMBase mailing lists can be found at the MMBase contact page: http://www.mmbase.org/contact. Subscription to the community@mmbase.org mailing list can be done at the MMBase contact page, or by sending an email to info@mmbase.org

</body>
		<title>community@mmbase.org</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>To enable the MMBase community to communicate easier, the MMC has created a new mailing list community@mmbase.org.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="35349" owner="admin">
		<body>For the department of Economic Affairs and Syntens a MMBase portal has been created to give companies more information about the advantages of Open Source Software (OASE project). For the department a special user friendly version of MMBase called MAG MMBase was created, so the communication department can easily update their portal.

MAG MMBase is an add-on for MMBase under the Mozilla license. MAG MMBase is especially made for marketing &amp; content managers with functions like MS office integration, Role based approval and staging and Live environments. It is compatible with future versions of MMBase without depending on the supplier of this addon.

&quot;The choice for MMBase was simple&quot; according to projectmanager Carlos dos Santos, &quot;We have chosen for the largest OSS project in the Netherlands. Which has outstanding credentials by government organisations and companies. So we are not the first using MMBase&quot; 

For more information: see the oaseproject on the website of Syntens, or turn to Mag productions. 

The improvements and new features MAG Productions made, will be available for all MMBase-users.  </body>
		<title>MMBase portal for Syntens</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>MAG Productions builds portal for innovation network of theDutch Ministry of Economic Affairs</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="39936" owner="admin">
		<body>More than 30 bugs have been fixed in this release and also a few performance issues have been resolved. See releasenotes.txt for the complete list of bugfixes.

Because an unicast implementation has been added besides the existing multicast implementation for broadcasting changes, you are required to make some configuration changes. Please refer to the upgrade.txt for information about these changes. </body>
		<title>MMBase-1.7.2 final release available</title>
		<subtitle>The second bugfix release for MMBase-1.7 is available.</subtitle>
		<intro>The MMBase developers team is proud to present the second bugfix release of MMBase-1.7.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="40666" owner="admin">
		<body>This bug (#6637: Query-caches are not invalidated correctly if queried on relation-object directly) resulted in problems with the editwizards.
The 1.7.3 release includes a bugfix for this problem and also includes a few more bugfixes, see releasenotes for more information.</body>
		<title>MMBase-1.7.3 final release available</title>
		<subtitle>The third (minor) bugfix release for MMBase-1.7 is available.</subtitle>
		<intro>Just a few days after the 1.7.2 release a rather nasty bug has been found and fixed.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="42531" owner="admin">
		<body>Last evening (17-02-2005) the Holland Open Software Platform (HOSP) was established at the premises of the Dutch broadcaster VPRO, who almost five years ago decided to make its content management system MMBase open source. So this is a very good environment for an important announcement, said Leon Gommans, board member of HOSP. Over 50 attendees to this version of the &quot;open software network meeting&quot; listened to the plans of the new Foundation that were presented by Leon Gommans and Jo Lahaye (MMBase Foundation), who also announced the plans for the first Holland Open Software Conference. 

The attendees were asked to join the initiatives, submit proposals for the Conference and help to design the organizational structure of the Foundation. Although the Foundation is already established, only the goal of the HOSP has been defined yet. &quot;And even this goal can be altered if a majority of you would ask us to do so,&quot; declared Lahaye. But instead there was an overwhelming support, for the four statements:

a. To advocate the use of open standards in all aspects of information technology, to improve open information-processing, as well as stimulating the use of open source software.
b. To look after the interests of all organisations, companies, perons and open source communities who support this aim.
c. To combine forces with the various local and sectoral initiatives and give them the means for exchanging knowledge, in all of its forms.
d. To function as a contact point for equal initiatives in other (European) countries.

Already, many organizations showed their support for the Conference and the idea of establishing a platform. if you would like to join, you are more than welcome. The MMBase Foundation thinks it is a good idea if there is a Dutch umbrella organization that actively promotes the use of open standards and stimulates open source initiatives and hopes that the Conference will be a great success. </body>
		<title>Holland Open Software Platform established</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>At the cradle of MMBase: The VPRO.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="46960" owner="default">
		<body>The history of MMBase, its main characteristics and future challenges are well described in the upcoming publication of the IBM Systems Journal. On the website the paper is already accessible. The IBM Systems Journal is one of the leading scientific papers on information technology. The Journal is published in hard copy (some 45.000) and downloadable from the website (over 120.000 visitors a month). 

Several members of the MMBase community worked very hard (in 2004) to get this paper written. The first version of the paper was reviewed by the editor in chief, David Seidman, who made serious comments. The second version was judged by four reviewers, who made many more remarks. But at that point, it became clear we had a good chance of getting the paper published. The remarks of the reviewers were on technological issues, unclear abbreviations, but no one suggested to reject the paper as a whole.

So there we are. MMBase, internationally in the spotlights. Let's see what happens. At least, we have an outstandig paper on our project. The MMBase Foundation that coordinated the writing, likes to thank all authors and the many developers and managers that helped bringing all information together.

Hope you enjoy reading &quot;MMBase, an open source content management system.&quot; 
 
co-editors who made many remarks, although they al said after the first round &quot;paper is well written and of interest&quot;. 

And now we are ofcourse very proud that the paper is actually there. 

Today, the scientific paper on MMBase was officially published on the website of IBM Systems Journal. I think it's great to have the history of MMBase, it's main chracteristics and some of the issues we're facing published on an international level.  


</body>
		<title>MMBase in IBM Systems Journal</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>MMBase is one of the open source projects in the Journal</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="47206" owner="default">
		<body>The next MMBase users &amp; developers meeting will be on Thursday May 19, 2005 - 19:00-21:00h (18:00h for those who join the pizza). The meeting is open to anyone who is interested in one of the topics.

The program of the meeting is now final:

1 - UML2MMBase - Ernst Bunders (15 min.)
UML2MMBase is a third-party application that generates a complete webapplication from a UML objectmodel. As a user of this tool, Ernst will give a demo and highlight its features.

2 - Introduction to Maven - Nico Klasens (30 min.)
Maven is  a software project management and comprehension tool that has recently beccome widely adopted. See: http://maven.apache.org. Now that an increasing number of separate modules of MMBase functionality is becoming available, a tool like Maven is needed to keep things managable. Nico Klasens will provide an introduction to Maven and tell about the experences he had while using Maven in projects (30 minutes).

3 - Richtext project - Michiel Meeuwisseen (&lt;15 minutes)
Status update. Michiel will explain why this project was recently re-opened.

4 - Optimization project - Pierre van Rooden (&lt;15 minutes)
Status update .


5 - Celebration of 5th anniversary of the MMBase Open Source project (20h15 - 21h00).
An informal, low-profile celebration - drinks and cake are provided for, sponsored by the VPRO.

The meeting will be hosted by the VPRO, at VPRO Digitaal. (For directions, see: http://www.vpro.nl/route.)

Pizza's are offered by the MMBase Foundation.

PLEASE, LET US KNOW IF YOU WANT TO ATTEND

If you would like to come to the meeting please send an email to robvanmaris@mmbase.org and fill in the questions below.

[ ] Yes, I will attend the users &amp; developers meeting of May 19
[ ] Yes, I arrive at 18:00h and please order a pizza for me. My favorite taste of pizza is ......
</body>
		<title>MMBase developer and user meeting Thursday May 19, 2005</title>
		<subtitle>The program of the meeting is now final!</subtitle>
		<intro>The next MMBase users &amp; developers meeting will be on Thursday May 19, 2005 - 19:00-21:00h (18:00h for those who join the pizza). The meeting is open to anyone who is interested in one of the topics.
</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="47252" owner="admin">
		<body>The lectures of the evening were:

Ernst Bunders (Vara) showed how a UML tool like Poseidon can be used to generate MMBase builders and edit wizards. Ernst created a class diagram with classes, relations and explained how UML2MMBase would translate this class diagram into MMBase builder and edit wizards.

Nico Klasens (Finalist) gave us a general understanding of Maven, which is a software project management tool. Differences between Ant and Maven were highlighted. Reasons why to use (or why not to use) Maven as a build tool for MMBase were addressed in his presentation.

Michiel Meeuwissen (Publieke Omroep- PO) told us why the Richtext project was reopened. Michiel also showed us some adoptions he already made in the standard MMBase editors.

Pierre van Rooden (Publieke Omroep - PO) told us that the optimization project is progressing slowly because not many developers are putting effort in this project.


Rob Vermeulen

Drink and cake were sponsored by the VPRO
pizzas were sponsored by the MMBase Foundation
</body>
		<title>MMBase Meeting / Lustrum</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The MMBase developers meeting was combined with a little party to celebrate 5th anniversary of MMBase. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="47662" owner="default">
		<body>At the annual meeting of the MMBase Foundation the board decided to research the position of MMBase because some people were suggesting the forecast was rather cloudy. The research was carried out by Ruben van Wendel de Joode, faculty of Organization &amp; Management, Delft Technical University. He wrote down the results in a paper called “A research concerning the continuity of the MMBase community”. The primary goal was to make clear what obstacles and possibilities lie ahead for further growth of MMBase. The gathering of data was done by interviewing 17 stakeholders: 7 committers, 4 end-users, 3 smaller vendors (&lt;50), 2 larger vendors (&gt;50) and the director of the Foundation. 

There is no full translation available, so we made a small summary. First of all, the paper is &quot;only&quot; offering an analysis of the situation, not a roadmap how to move on! That is what we have to do now: developers, users, vendors and the Foundation together. The full paper is attached, Dutch only. On Friday September 30 (from 15.00 hours), we will discuss how to move on. You can send your contribution, based on this paper (so please let's take the results for granted) with suggestions for (concrete) improvements to Jo@mmbase.org. This might be ideas that already came up and were for example discussed on the developers mailinglist. 

Summary:
First of all a Strengths Weaknesses Opportunities Threats-analysis (SWOT) was carried out concerning both the product MMBase and the MMBase community. The strengths that were considered to be the most important are: object orientation, Java, open source, Dutch character, strong customers, no lock in, etc. As weaknesses mostly the absence of several (default) functional characteristics of MMBase (workflow, versioning,...) were mentioned, besides this also process and organizational aspects of the community were stated. There was a lot of differentiation in the answer concerning the opportunities of MMBase. But most mentioned was the cooperation with (large) commercial vendors who can contribute to MMBase. Of the 17 people interviewed, 9 said that the biggest thread MMBase is facing are internal disagreements. 

In the paper there are many questions concerning which developers and organizations are important for the community. And further on, which role they should play. Most respondents think that MMBase is well able to compete with other CMS’s, they claim that it is technically in good order. Although one should notice that MMBase is, by most members (of the technical) community, not seen as a CMS but more like a CMS/portal toolkit. When asked about aspects that should be changed, most respondents answered that the core of MMBase should be improved as well as CMS-specific functionality like workflow, versioning, etc.

When it comes to suggestions for improvements, a long list of different ideas where offered, but with little consensus at this point. 

Other Questions were about the future, further growth and role of the MMBase community and the Foundation. 

In his conclusion the author states some subjects that clearly came forward during his research:
-The lack of unity within the MMBase community is considered an important threat. This leads to much debate which slows down the development of MMBase.
-The most important strengths are flexibility of the system because of the object orientation and the fact that it is Java based.
-Most respondents are satisfied with the technical status of MMBase: it is well able to compete with other CMS’s, but have to acknowledge that MMBase is not really a CMS. Most suggested improvements have the goal of transforming MMBase into a complete CMS by improving workflow, versioning and the templating system.
-People are satisfied about the technical system and are convinced that, because MMBase is open source, important difficulties will be overcome. The question therefore is whether there should be done something about technical aspects like workflow and versioning.
-There is a big threshold to contribute to MMBase for people that are not committers. 
-An important change that is suggested by a lot of respondents is to give MMBase a modular structure. MMBase should have a little core with a lot of products surrounding it. This simplifies things for people who want to contribute. In principal the committers should only be responsible for the core of MMBase. This could mean that there will be less discussions about the development and could even speed op the development.
-A lot of the respondents indicate that they miss a roadmap for the next version of MMBase. There is no clear vision of where MMBase should be going or is going.
</body>
		<title>Paper on the continuity of the MMBase community</title>
		<subtitle>Research by Ruben van Wendel de Joode, TU Delft.</subtitle>
		<intro>A research carried out by Ruben van Wendel de Joode, TU Delft. Debate on the paper September 30, 15.00 hours, TU Delft.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="47819" owner="admin">
		<body>The project adds a way to create startegies wich better the way MMBase uses and invalidates the query cache (which holds the results of previous database queries).
It also looks closer to the way events involving database changes are communicated between differnt MMbase instances.

More information can be obtained on the Query Cache Project page.</body>
		<title>Query Cache Project Started</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>A new MMBase project has been started, to improve the performance of MMBase caches by providing a cache strategy framework. 
</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="47997" owner="admin">
		<body>One of the most noticably new features is the ability to serve images from a different server. Some of the new 'imaging' features were backported from 1.8.

MMBase is distributed as a webapplication, it's not packaged as a WAR file, but the structure is the same. The distribution contains a complete running version of MMBase upon a hsql database with several editors and some example applications. If you are familiar with Java application servers you can just drop the 'mmbase-webapp' directory in you server's webapp directory and restart: MMBase will be running in several seconds.
Read the installation notes about configuring the webapplication and other installation options.

Please note that there have been some changes regarding the included XML jar's xalan.jar, xerces.jar en xml-apis.jar. We now believe that in order to run MMBase only xalan.jar needs to be included in the /WEB-INF/lib directory, depending on your application server of course. When you use Tomcat 5.5 you need to do nothing. When you run Tomcat 5.0 on JDK 1.4 you need to move the *.renametojar files to [tomcat-dir]/common/endorsed/*.jar. See the release notes and the in the /WEB-INF/lib included XERCES.README.txt file for more information. We be glad to hear about experiences with other application servers then Tomcat.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.7.4 released</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>After some time we have finally released MMBase 1.7.4. It contains numerous bugfixes and a few new features. See: download section.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="48343" owner="admin">
		<body>Based on MMBase, cultural centre De Balie developed the MMBase-application CultureBase. This is a presentation and publication application for cultural and not-for-profit organisations. CultureBase is an editorial system, built to tailor the enormously wide functionality of MMBase to the needs and wishes of cultural organisations with regularly changing live-programming. This is a whole new application field in which the possibilities for active ‘live’ public-participation in actual cultural programming are being realised. Central in this application is the connection between archive- and publication functions on internet together with live elements. De Balie was the first to start with using this very advanced software technology. Now De Melkweg has given live to this technology, too. 

Open source technology is explicitly chosen for this development; by giving the results back to the open source community, in the Netherlands primarily via the MMBase community, also the technically more advanced resolutions will find their way into society. All knowledge and experience gained through this way of developing will have its effect on cultural institutions as much as on the open source community around MMBase, and with this community on a growing number of public institutions like governments and broadcasting services.</body>
		<title>New website De Melkweg based on MMBase online</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>This month, De Melkweg has switched the servers. The new and improved website is now running on the open source Content Management System MMBase.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="48430" owner="admin">
		<body>De verschillende producten, kostensoorten en polissen van de zorgverzekeraars worden nu aan elkaar gekoppeld en vergeleken. Recentelijk werd uit onderzoek van de Consumentenbond duidelijk dat er een grote behoefte is aan heldere informatie over polissen en producten. Tevens overweegt een groot percentage consumenten te kiezen voor een nieuwe verzekeraar per 1 januari 2006. Het IMS van Zorgweb ondersteunt consumenten bij de oriëntatie op het nieuwe aanbod van zorgverzekeringen en stelt hen in staat om overzichtelijk een goede keuze te kunnen maken voor de zorgverzekering en verzekeraar die bij hen past. 

Informatie management systeem
De informatie voor verschillende vergelijkingssites wordt door de onderneming Mag productions uit Enschede aangeboden aan onder meer Independer (www.independer.nl), RIVM (www.kiesbeter.nl) en KWIZ (vergoeding.net). Deze partijen integreren de data uit het IMS van Zorgweb in hun eigen systeem. Voor deze integratie maakt men gebruik van de portal integration technologie van Mag productions, die is ontwikkeld in MMBase en de AJAX-techniek. MMBase is een webgebaseerd  'open source'-systeem voor het creëren, beheren en presenteren van informatie.  De AJAX-methode is een techniek voor het ontwerpen van interactieve webpagina's waarin asynchroon gevraagde gegevens worden opgehaald van de webserver. Voordeel hiervan is dat de integratie van de informatie veel sneller verloopt (real time) en dat webpagina's niet meer ververst hoeven te worden. Het IMS is een Informatie Management Systeem waarin verschillende producten, kostensoorten en zorgverzekeraars aan elkaar gekoppeld kunnen worden. Op die manier kunnen zorgverzekeringen en zorgverzekeraars via een webgebaseerd IMS aangeboden worden

Noot voor de redactie
Voor meer informatie:

magproductions
Martijn Verhoeven
7500 AK Enschede 
T: 053-4346874
M: 06-26868939
I: www.magproductions.nl
E: martijn@magproductions.nl 

Zorgweb b.v.
Peter Zuidhof
De Hanekampen 16
9411 XM Beilen
T: 0593 - 552867 
E: peter.zuidhof@bsenf.nl
</body>
		<title>Vergelijking nieuwe zorgverzekeringen eenvoudig (Dutch only)</title>
		<subtitle>Nieuwe technologie en innovatie biedt consumenten kansen</subtitle>
		<intro>Een nieuw informatie management systeem heeft de vergelijking van zorgverzekeringen bij het RIVM en Independer vanaf vandaag een stuk eenvoudiger en overzichtelijker gemaakt.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="48456" owner="admin">
		<body>Several show-stoppers can still be thought off, it is not a candidate for release. The weak points are to be found in areas like application export/import,  more advanced datatypes (like 'confirm password'), and perhaps the packaging of the distro itself.

This beta is to encourage people to look into it.  Issues can be discussed on the mailing list, in the bugtracker, or on IRC #mmbase.
</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8.0 beta</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>All automated junit tests succeed. To celebrate this, CVS Head is tagged with MMBase-1_8_0_beta. Available under MMBase builds in the download section of this website.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="48542" owner="default">
		<body>As most of you know, a lot of people and organizations participated in 2005 in the debate on the future of MMBase. There were -and are- many different views on the road ahead. In the autumn of 2004 this led to the conclusion that if we want to move ahead, we need a board that represents the whole community: developers, users and technical partners. At the annual meeting of the MMBase Foundation (December 2005) a concrete proposal to install a board was discussed and approved. The developers proposed two candidates, as did the users and technical partners. These persons ‘represent’ their colleagues. The Foundation acts as host and guides the process. 

The members of the technical board are (on behalf of):  
- developers: Michiel Meeuwissen and Daniel Ockeloen.
- users: Ronald Vendelmans (Amsterdam), Nadia Poulou (Kennisnet)
- service providers: Jean-Luc van Hulst (Finalist ), Henk Hangyi (MMatch).
- foundation: Jo Lahaye. 

In the attachement the minutes of the first meeting. If you have any questions, don't hesitate to contact the Foundation: Jo@mmbase.org. 

Your input is of course very welcome! 
</body>
		<title>First meeting technical board</title>
		<subtitle>Minutes: agenda set and first deliverables</subtitle>
		<intro>Minutes: agenda set for the coming period and agreement on first deliverables  </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="49449" owner="default">
		<body>Today 9 developers have been working hard to fix bug in the 1.8 release of MMBase. Open issues include: (1) exporting and importing data via apps1 (showstopper), (2) bug in transaction, (3) choices about what has to be included in the distro (e.g. including two taglib.jars and what do we have to do with packaging). Next week friday (March 31) the first release candidate is planned.
</body>
		<title>Bugfix day: 27 bugs fixed!</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>First release candidate planned for next week.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="49654" owner="default">
		<body>Meetings technical board
There are no minutes of the second and fourth meeting. These meetings were used to discuss several ideas concerning the road ahead. In the 3rd meeting we discussed how to set up an architectureal model. We decided to use the Kennisnet method (see minutes of third meeting).

The fourth meeting we were incomplete, discussed several issues, but without any clear decissions. The minutes of the fifth meeting are attached.

Members of the technical committee:
Nadia Poulou (Kennisnet)
Ronald Vendelmans (Amsterdam)
Jean-Luc van Hulst (Finalist)
Henk Hangyi (Mmatch)
Daniel Ockeloen (MMCoder)
Michiel Meeuwissen (PO)
Jo Lahaye (foundation)

In the attachment the minutes of the third and fifth meeting. If you have any questions, don't hesitate to contact the foundation: Jo@mmbase.org.

In another attachment, Nadia’s presentation and the enclosed time schedule

Your input is of course very welcome!</body>
		<title>Third-fifth meeting technical board</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Meetings technical board; The cms container data model and the application for component based development. 
</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="49974" owner="default">
		<body>This weekend releasemanager Michiel Meeuwissen finished the last tests and defeated the last bugs.
During the past weeks several bugs were fixed on the new features (mainly datatypes). It costed more time than we anticipated. There are still a few issues which needed to be fixed before the final release, like for example bug #6801.

RC1 is available for download at the download section or the releases page. MMBase 1.8.0 will propbabely be released in a couple of weeks.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8.0 rc1</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>May 1: Release candidate 1.8.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="50090" owner="default">
		<body>MMBase 1.8 can be found in the download section at this website or by using one of the links above.

Optimization
Since the release of MMBase 1.7 and some bugfix release since then, MMBase developers have continuously been working on the improvement of the core within the scope if the optimization and cleaning project. The result of these efforts:
- more API documentation and overall application of code conventions;
- the last lines of lingering VPRO code have been removed, the templating system SCAN is completely moved to a separate application;
- the removement and deprecation of code and unused functionality, classes and configuration files;
- the removal of SQL queries to the database packages;
- the merge of all code presently in the ObjectTypes builder or the TypeDef builder making ObjectTypes obsolete;
- internationalisation of messages; and
- creation of tools to monitor the performance of MMBase like MMBar;
Resulting in a cleaner, leaner core, and a better performing MMBase.

Datatypes
Fields of MMBase nodes could formally only be of the following types: string, integer, byte array, float, double, long, xml and node. With datatypes new types were introduced: boolean and datetimes. Byte array is now known as binary. 
The most important change though is that datatypes are completely pluggable and configurable. It supports 'restrictions' on all types, default values, uniqueness etc.on field level. For example you can specify in a builder that a specific field only may contain an email address or for example that the date a user may enter only may be a future date. Editor implementations of these functionalities are now being developed.

Caching
MMBase supports now a cache release framework in which the evaluation of changes to the cache can be configured for any specific web application. For example when you post a message in a forum it is unnecessary to invalidate all forum posts. In the new implementation the cache can be configured to invalidate the cache of only that single thread to which the message was posted.
Besides that the MMBase's cache can be configured to make use of OSCache an thus profiting of the popular OSCache caching code with the new MMBase OSCache application. OSCache enables you for example to allow your cache to overflow to disk.

Taglib
Several new tags and attributes to existing tags were made. A main improvement is that MMBase is now compatible with Expression Language: MMBase taglib variables are now EL variables. This may give minor compatibility issues but you can switch this behaviour off. 
'Escapers' can be more easily added, and they can also be configured on the page (see mm:escaper). The EditTag is a new tag that enables you to create an url to an editor using the data provided in the nodes and fields in a page. Consult the documentation for a complete overview of all new features of the taglib.

Other features
The Resource Manager is introduced. MMBase can now be more easily be deployed as WAR now. Most configuration can also be shipped inside jars, and be overriden. This means the most applications can principally be installed by placing one JAR in WEB-INF/lib plus placing the needed JSP's if any.
Several image improvements were made, like specifying height and width of an image and the ability to set up separate image server. And the filename of upload can be stored, and thus can be added to the URL.
A new Richtext application providing support for the kupu-editor enabling 'rich text' including inline urls, attachments, images, cross-links and 'blocks' (notes, intermezzo's).
The function framework is completed. Among others you can now add functions in the builder without the need to override the builder class if it has one.
Some new applications are added to MMBase in the form of contributions, like for example ASelect, MMBob and a Lucene search application.

And more
An overview of all changes and improvements can be found in the MMBase documentation &lt;http://www.mmbase.org/mmdocs/&gt; and the release notes. 
</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8 released!</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Today the MMBase community released 1.8.0., a long awaited and major release, with many new features: optimized and cleaner code, new datatypes and improvements on fields, new taglib features, configurable caching mechanisms, RichText and many other functionalities.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="50417" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<title>Release 1.9 discussed on the developers meeting at the Holland Open Software Conference</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The active projects which will be become part of the MMBase 1.9 release were discussed on the developers meeting at the Holland Open Source Congres.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="50516" owner="default">
		<body>On behalf of the technical committee the MMBase Foundation is looking for a release manager. The releasemanager has to be fluent in English and Dutch. We are looking for a projectmanager with knowledge of MMBase development, or an MMBase developer who is also capable of managing projects. If you already have a job, but you would like to combine this function, please contact the Foundation, to see if arrangements with your management can be made. The foundation and representatives from the technical committee will talk with candidates in the first two weeks of september. If you are interested, or know someone who might be interested, please send an email tot the Foundation. The contract will (initially) be for 1 year. 
Job description in Dutch below: 

-Maakt een planning voor releases, zowel minor als major 
-Coordineert met de developers en in overleg met het technisch comité wat er in een release komt en ziet er op toe dat mensen zich hier aan houden. Hij (zij) is dus streng als het er om gaat niet geplande onderdelen of wijzigingen toe te staan. 
-Beheert de (JIRA) bugtracker en zorgt ervoor dat niet alleen de bugs maar ook de ten behoeve van die release lopende projecten worden bijgehouden. 
-Documenteert en test zelf onderdelen of regelt in overleg met het technisch comité en/of Stichting resources voor testing en documentatie. 
Profiel 
Het gaat om een persoon met de volgende eigenschappen, competenties:
-technisch projectmanager met ervaring in software ontwikkeltrajecten 
-affiniteit met techniek, eventueel met een achtergrond in softwareontwikkeling 
-proactief en pragmatisch, meer dan procedureeel. 
-kan werken in 'less than ideal' omstandigheden 
-is gewend om met remote teamleden te werken waarbij veel communicatie via mail en andere kanalen gaat en relatief weinig via direct handson contact.
-Spreekt en schrijft vloeiend (technisch) Engels en Nederlands. 
Belangstellenden kunnen zich melden bij de Stichting. Er wordt uitgegaan dat deze werkzaamheden een dag per week in beslag zullen nemen. De honorering / vergoeding is vastgesteld op 1000 euro per maand op declaratie basis (dus 12.000 euro per jaar). Deze functie kan ook worden verricht door een werknemer van een van de partners.
 
Jo Lahaye,
27 juni 2006</body>
		<title>Job opportunity: MMBase release manager</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>On behalf of the technical committee the MMBase Foundation is looking for a release manager.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="50660" owner="default">
		<body>MMBase 1.7.5 is a bugfix release of the former main MMBase release. It contains a fix for a nasty bug in the editwizards that prevented them from running on Tomcat 5.5 and Java 1.5 and some other minor fixes.

The first bugfix release of MMBase 1.8 sports some major performance and memory improvements, and some minor others. A more complete overview can be read in the release-notes. An overview:

- the implementation of PostgreSQL's support for views, 
- several small taglib improvements, like mm:mayread, an easier to use when reusing the request (dynamic includes), JSP variables on querycontainers, timezones on locale-tags a style class on mm:form, 
- improved date-parsing and 
- the clustering implementations have been reviewed, adding e.g. 'admin pages' for clustering.</body>
		<title>Developers release two: 1.7.5 and 1.8.1</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Today is a great day indeed since the MMBase developers community released two bugfix releases.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="50805" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<title>Meeting of the technical board, Sept 12, 2006</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Last week wednessday there was a meeting of the technical board. The minutes of the meeting are now online.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51353" owner="default">
		<body>During one of our last projectmeetings of the MMBase Component Framework project we thought it a good idea to organize a programming 'weekend' (friday 13th and saturday 14th) to make some significant progress with the new components and the framework that will harbor them. I've asked around a little and this seems to be a good date. We possibly start around 10 friday, code and discuss until diner, code and discuss again until very, very late, get some sleep (or not), and start coding again saturday morning and the afternoon probably till diner. I trust that the MMBase foundation provides the catering...

The 'weekend' will be held in Hilversum at the MMBase Foundation, Neuweg 83, 1214 GM Hilversum (035-6288088 or call me for questions +31 (0)627233562). Sleeping will be quite basic but i think it will also be possible to have a few people sleep at my place or someone else's living in Hilversum.

Anybody who wants to join and thinks that she/he can make a contribution is most welcome.
</body>
		<title>Development weekend MMBase Component Framework</title>
		<subtitle>Friday October 13 (!) and Saturday 14th.</subtitle>
		<intro>If you would like to join, please send an e-mail to Andre van Toly (andre at toly dot nl) or the Foundation (jo at mmbase dot org). </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51407" owner="default">
		<body>The release team today released the second bugfix release of MMBase 1.8. An overview of the bugs that were fixed can be found in the bugtracker.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8.2 released</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Second bugfix release of MMBase 1.8</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51564" owner="default">
		<body>After a few &quot;simple tests&quot;, at 5 pm the first &quot;more complex&quot; component, an e-card functionality, works properly on newly build framework architecture. Reason enough to open a bottle of champagne. At the picture you see Nico Klasens, André van Toly, Johannes Verelst (all standing), Michiel Meeuwissen and Henk Hangyi at the office of the MMBase Foundation. Due to other obligations Arjen Roodselaar had just left the office. Jo Lahaye spend his time in making sandwiches, pouring coffee and other drinks, to make sure everyone was comfortable. 

The coding weekend endend Saturday evening at 11 pm, after a good meal in a nearby restaurant. Everyone left with the feeling the progress made is very stimulating. And of course the start of the weekend was -although on Friday the 13th- exciting as well: Kennisnet surpised us with a very special whipped cream cake. After a short night (people worked till far after midnight on friday), everyone was steaming up again around 10.30 a.m on Saturday. 

For technical information on this project please see the project-pages.

In brief, the idea is that if we want to share components on top of MMBase, we need a framework that makes it easy to develop components in a structured way. At this moment, many large applications have their own poll, forum, e-card, webshop, but most of these functionalities are application-specific. For that reason, it was not very easy to (for example) use the webshop of Natuurmonumenten in another MMBase implementation.

Several Organizations allready said that they are willing to invest time (and money) to make their functionalities &quot;framework compatible&quot;, so many features will be available on short notice. By the way, existing applications don't have to be seriously refactured to start using the framework. More information will be available soon. 
</body>
		<title>Breaktrough at Component Framework coding weekend</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Johannes Verelst reports a breakthrough at 5 p.m. on Saturday.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51726" owner="default">
		<body>After the productive weekend in October and the constantly growing enthusiasm of Michiel, we would like to organize another component framework weekend on Friday 8 th and Saturday 9 th of December.

Goal of the weekend is to:
1. link the CMSC to the component framework: it should be possible to use components as portlets in the CMSC, and the otherway around to use portlets as components in the component framework,
2. create new components from already existing pieces of functionality (or from scratch if you like to),
3. extend the component framework where needed.

The 'weekend' will be held in Hilversum at the MMBase Foundation, Neuweg 83, 1214 GM Hilversum (035-6288088 or call Andre for questions +31 (0)627233562). A basic sleeping place is guaranteed, but most probably we will manage to get you a descent bed. Food and drinks are offered by the MMBase Foundation.

Everybody who would like to join and create his/her first components is welcome! You can also join for one day. Please send an e-mail to Andre van Toly (andre@toly.nl) or the Foundation (jo@mmbase.org).
</body>
		<title>Join the Component Framework weekend</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Building components and extending the brand new component framework on Friday 8th and Saturday 9th of December...</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51733" owner="default">
		<body>On Thursday 14 December there will be a special developers meeting on the CMS Container. People who would like to get an introduction into working with the CMSC and have some handson experience with developing are welcome from 9:00-13:30h. The workshop will be given by Nico Klasens.

The workshop will be held in Hilversum, so you can also join the MMBase Annual meeting which takes place at the VPRO building in the afternoon (from 14:00h). The exact location of the developers meeting will be communicated later. Please email to hangyi@xs4all or phone with +31 (0)629054903 in case of questions and if you would like to attend the workshop.

Don't forget to bring a notebook with enough free disk space to install the CMSC ;)
</body>
		<title>CMS Container Workshop</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Using the CMSC and develop your own portlets on Thursday 14 December ...</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51741" owner="default">
		<body>The Annual Meeting of the MMBase Foundation will be held on Thursday December 14, 2006 at the VPRO from 14:00-18:00h. Presentations will be given by Lucas Vroemen of the regional broadcasting organization Limburg L1, the community of Nijmegen and several other organizations who started to use MMBase in 2006. And of course there are also presentations on the new developments that will be incorporated in the MMBase 2.0 release, like the CMS Container and the component framework. Entrance is free, but please register: jo@mmbase.org
</body>
		<title>MMBase Annual Meeting</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Join the annual meeting Thursday December 14, 2006 at the VPRO to find out what happened in 2006 and is planned for 2007.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51776" owner="default">
		<body>The minutes of the meeting of the MMBase technical board are now online.</body>
		<title>Meeting of the technical board, Nov 16, 2006</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro></intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51862" owner="default">
		<body>The former release was two months ago. Since then several more bugs were fixed, enough to justify a new release.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8.3 released</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Sinterklaas brought us a new release, it can be downloaded in the download section.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51874" owner="default">
		<body>Progress has been made on the component admin environment, the technical specification of window-states, and the javadoc of the main component framework classes. A big new breakthrough was realized by Nico who managed to render components inside a portlet in the CMS Container. In this way it is possible to (re)use present and new components in the CMS Container. 
Johannes is thinking of making more Didactor&quot; technology available as Framework-components in the coming periode. Didactor is the MMBase e-learning environment. We hope that in the upcoming period a lot of users and service provideers will start to use the componentframework. For new applications, but hopefully also to refactor existing technologies. So we hope that a lot of components will be available in a short time. 


 </body>
		<title>Components as portlets in the CMS Container</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>In the weekend of 8-th and 9-th of December a lot of work was carried out on improving the component framework.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51889" owner="default">
		<body>The e-learning software Didactor was used succesfully in training managers of small and medium size enterprises (SME's) about the benefits of Open Source Software. A consortium of many European partners researched the possibility of setting up an online training programme and the effectiveness of such an online tool, without any classroom or teacher in sight. The response was above all expectations, as most of the trainees were rather positive about this online program. In the enclosed document you cab find the eveluation report of this (partly) EU funded Leonardo project. Please visit the Stratos website for more information about the project. </body>
		<title>Didactor succesfully used for training managers on Open source Software</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro> Succesfull EU project for managers ended, possible follow up.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="51986" owner="default">
		<body>Present: Martijn (MAG Productions), Wessel (MAG Productions), Andre (Andre), Henk (Finalist), Eduard (Yacht), Nico (Finalist), Wouter (Wouter), Ernst (Dynasol), Michiel (Publieke Omroep / Dynasol), Johannes (EO).

*** 1. status of component framework

Todo's for 1.9:
-security &lt;mm:may action=&quot;..&quot;/&gt; and &lt;mm:setting name=&quot;..&quot; /&gt;
-processor
-directory layout, at least for created components + migration description
-testing
-bugs: redirect, url generation

Desision:
Plan component days: 1 friday every 3 weeks untill 1.9 release, preferably in combination with Kennisnet project

Johannes - add securities ideas
Henk - plan component days
Andre - reviews documentation

*** 2. the migration of the MMBase core to Java 1.5

NodeList will become deprecated (in 1.9, maybe removed in 2.0) and replaced by List from Node. Some code examples:

&gt;&gt; 1.8:
NodeList list = cloud.getList(QUERY)\

&gt;&gt; head:
NodeList&lt;Node&gt; list = cloud.getList...


BasicNodeList implements NodeList&lt;Node&gt; extends ArrayList {
   BasicNopdeList(Collection c) {
      super(c);
   }
}


&gt;&gt; 1.9:
MMList&lt;Node&gt; list = cloud.getList();
List&lt;Relation&gt; list = node.getRelations();
List&lt;NodeManager&gt; list = node.getNodeManager();

Nico and Michiel - make an appointment for a Java 5 saturday to see if NodeList&lt;Node&gt; can be removed from head.

*** 3. release planning with Jira

All commits should have a Jira issue number, except: typos, code conventions, log message changes.

Henk and Nico - clean up Unscheduled

*** 4. release possibilities of applications/extensions

Decisions:

- HEAD of applications / contributions always compiles with HEAD of MMBase if you use Ant. Solution: nightly build stays in Ant, but maven scripts for contributions use outcomes of build by Ant.

- branches/tags of MMBase (ALL) and branches of contributions independent. See MMBob in Jira as example.

*** 5. implementing transactions in MMBase

In the present situation, every update causes the caches to refresh. Also in the core, cloud should be a transaction.

Step2: the transaction functionality in the editwizards and the bridge can then be removed.

MMBase project, projectmanager Nico, document by Nico will be elaborated, planned for release 2.0.</body>
		<title>Developers meeting, 24.01.2007</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The minutes of the developers meeting. 

Next meeting: Thursday March 8, 2007.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52003" owner="default">
		<body>At the last developers meeting we decided to plan a sequence of fridays at which the component framework projectteam will work on extending and testing the MMBase component framework. The goal is to speed up development and get ready for the MMBase 2.0 release.

The dates planned are:

Friday February 9
Friday March 2
Friday March 30
Friday April 13
Friday May 4
Friday May 25
Friday June 15

If you think that you should be part of the team and would like to join Friday in developing and testing the component framework, feel free to contact hangyi@xs4all.nl</body>
		<title>Component framework fridays</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Get ready for 2.0!</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52015" owner="default">
		<body>At the first Component Framework Friday the first component living happily in the CMS Container was spotted. To be more specific the crontab component created by Michiel nicely popped up as a Pluto portlet conforming the JSR 168 standard. Click on the image to see the evidence ;) Next to this Nico also reported to have the basic component framework and the CMS Container operating side be side in one web application.

The other way around creating portlets that also run as components in the component framework is a different story. Check the component framework documentation (see the link above, the section on using portlets as components) for further information on this topic.

The next Component Framework Friday will be March 30, so more news can be expected around that time. </body>
		<title>Components live happily in the CMS Container</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro></intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52396" owner="default">
		<body>The editors are completely rewritten from the ground up in XHTML 1.0 strict to be even more user and browser friendly. They make use of some of the latest features of the MMBase taglib. Besides they now sport some useful javascripts to enable easier ways to find and edit data.

Not all new features of the MMBase taglib were included. Stuff that still needs to be implemented are for example the functionalities to validate user input by using the new &lt;mm:form /&gt; and &lt;mm:validate /&gt; tags. Another still to be implemented feature could be the inclusion of an HTML-editor.

The editors can be found in cvs HEAD or can be downloaded from André van Toly's website. They are written for MMBase 1.9 but are compatible with MMBase 1.8.</body>
		<title>New version of my_editors</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>A few days ago a new, completely revised version of the generic userfriendly MMBase editors named my_editors was placed in cvs.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52417" owner="default">
		<body>Present: Andre (Andre), Henk (Finalist), Nico (Finalist), Wouter (Wouter), Ernst (Dynasol), Michiel (Dynasol), Pierre (Publieke Omroep), Johannes (EO), Jo (Foundation)

----

The following items where discussed during the meeting:

A. News
B. What can go wrong migration to 1.8
C. Current issues
D. Roadmap
E. Mailinglist

A. News

1. MMBase website is now on 1.8
2. principle tracker on line
3. generic portlets of CMS Container are now in the MMBase CVS 
4. new version my_editors http://www.toly.nl

B. What can go wrong migration to 1.8.

The following issues were reported and discussed during the meeting:

0. of course the items in the release notes (5 items) a.o. security api has been changed, so specific security implementations have to be migrated
1. nodelist providers (e.g. relatednodes) do not provide their own context (not in jira)
2. dynamic includes the active escaper, locales, etc remains active, so things that where not escaped previously are now escaped
3. jspvars in taglibs are imported in the page context
4. incorrect builder xmls now give error messages (better than correct is to rewrite to 1.8 standard e.g. WiaB)
5. api changes, but this turns out be a minor thing in most cases

C. Current issues:

- since 1.8.3 serialisation (happens when restarting Tomcat) gives a number of problems: entries in typedef table get duplicated, an extra MMBase is started and 401.

- Java 1.5: RMMCI does not compile at the moment. Nico will have a serious look at it also on two problems with serialisation and generics.

D. The MMBase Roadmap was discussed.

http://www.mmbase.org/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10000

A note was made that the CMS Container is not part of the roadmap of MMBase, but will be released at the same time MMBase 1.9.

E. Mailinglists:

The following cleaning actions should be carried out:
- refresh the list of committers
- ask rico / justin for mailinglist passwords
- info#mmbase.org (remove cc-s), community#mmbase.org, committers#mmbase.org, announce#mmbase.org, mmc#mmbase.org: only announce#mmbase.org remains and all email addresses are moved to this list; info@mmbase.org will be the owner of the list  

Jo makes a proposal for cleaning up the mailing lists.</body>
		<title>Developers meeting, 08.03.2007</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Minutes of the MMBase developer meeting. Next meeting is May 10.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52481" owner="default">
		<body>User days give a platform to the users of the CMS Container to talk about their experiences, fix plans for upcoming releases, and discuss new functionality. Yesterday the main topics were: release planning, the new online platform www.cmscontainer.org and the new logo for the CMS Container. See also the program of the meeting. Due to the sunny weather Coenen was a perfect place to finish the meeting and drink a toast on the future. The next meeting is on June 26, 2007 at Almere.

</body>
		<title>First CMS Container User Day</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Yesterday April the 24-th 2007 the first CMS Container user day toke place at the NAi (Dutch Architecture Institute).</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52498" owner="default">
		<body>Today is an historical day for MMBase as we have moved our build process from Ant to Maven. It has been 2 years ago that Maven was first discussed at the 5-th anniversary of MMBase. For the component framework release the Maven build means that we have an up to date overview of the components in the MMBase source repository. The next component framework fridays are Friday May 25 and Friday June 15.</body>
		<title>MMBase moves to Maven</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Twenty days before its 7-th anniversary MMBase moves to Maven !</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52566" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8.4 released</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Bugfix release fixes and improves upon 54 issues.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52663" owner="default">
		<body>Next meeting is September 13.

Present:

André van Toly
Michiel Meeuwissen
Jo Lahaye
Johannes Verelst
Pierre van Rooden
Henk Hangyi

The following new features in MMBase 1.8 were demonstrated and discussed:


A. Taglib side of datatypes (Michiel)

&lt;mm:form&gt;
&lt;mm:fieldinfo type=&quot;input&quot;&gt;
&lt;mm:fieldinfo type=&quot;error&quot;&gt;
&lt;mm:valid&gt;

***
B. New taglib features (André)

&lt;mm:compare regexp=&quot;^&lt;p&gt;.*&quot;&gt;

&lt;mm:formater&gt;
   &lt;mm:write referid=&quot;rss&quot;&gt;
   &lt;mm:xslt&gt;
      ...  to use xslt in jsp templates ...
   &lt;/mm:xslt&gt;
&lt;/mm:formater&gt;

&lt;mm:escaper type=&quot;substring&quot; id=&quot;substr&quot;&gt;
   &lt;mm:param name=&quot;from&quot;&gt;0&lt;/mm:param&gt;
   &lt;mm:param name=&quot;to&quot;&gt;14&lt;/mm:param&gt;
   &lt;mm:param name=&quot;elipsis&quot;&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/mm:param&gt;
&lt;/mm:escaper&gt;

&lt;mm:write escape=&quot;trimmer,substring(0,12,&amp;hellip;)&quot;

---
Expression language:

${mm:escape}
${mm:directory}
${mm:contains}
${_node.title}

---
Mixing types:

&lt;mm:listnodes type=&quot;images,attachments&quot;&gt;

---
Time parsing

****
C. The technical terms on the website are found by Google

The more general terms will be added to the title/description/keywords of pages.

E.g. java open source content management system

Action: Johannes


</body>
		<title>Developers meeting, 28.06.2007</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Minutes of the MMBase developer meeting.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52788" owner="default">
		<body>The Technical Board of MMBase releases the first draft of the architectural principles. In the past months the members of the technical board worked on a first version of 15 principles, that combined give a good insight in the do's and dont's. We hope the principles will be discussed in depth, so they can be improved. And the number of principles might grow as developers and users might see other issues that need to be addressed. Feedback is welcome, now and in future, as we do all understand that with the continuous developmet of MMBase, some principles are due to change or become (ir-)relevant.

We tried to describe the principles in a structured way (thanks to Kennisnet, especially Nadia Poulou, Rob de Bruin and Arjan van Krimpen). Some principles we classified as “binding”, others as a “strong rule”, meaning you better listen. The consequences are described as well as to which part the principle applies to (core, framework, components).  

Have a look, send your comments, suggestions or other remarks to Jo@mmbase.org.

</body>
		<title>Principles describe MMBase architecture</title>
		<subtitle>Technical Board presents 15 -to be discussed- principles</subtitle>
		<intro>Technical Board presents 15 -to be discussed- principles</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52928" owner="default">
		<body>This is a follow-up bugfix release upon MMBase 1.8.4, since which more than 50 bugs were fixed and several wishes were granted. And also between rc1 and this release a few more issues were found and fixed.

One of the main new features in this release is a Javascript framework for the datatypes MMBase supports since 1.8. Using a asynchronous validation library (ajax) you can now validate form field inputs against their datatypes. See for example the taglib documentation and http://www.mmbase.org/mmdocs/informationanalysts/datatypes.html#taglib for more information.

The 1.8.5 version of MMBase is the first distro of MMBase which is partly compiled with Java 1.5. These are the following shipped applications: lucene, email, crontab, mmbob which are taken from CVS HEAD, and are no more maintained in the 1.8 branch of MMBase itself.

We don't build documentation any more, we refer to http://www.mmbase.org/mmdocs for up-to-date version of the documentation, or the build of HEAD for a downloadable version.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8.5 released</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>A main new feature is a Javascript validation framework for MMBase datatypes. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="52981" owner="default">
		<body></body>
		<title>2008 the year of MMBase 1.9</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>2008 will be the year in which MMBase 1.9 will be released. To celebrate this, there was a new-years-drink on January the 25-th.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53005" owner="default">
		<body>The MMCF projectteam is working hard to get ready for the 1.9 release. The framework interface and the basic framework are implemented. The work which remains to be done is testing the integration of the CMSc, Didactor, finishing the component framework admin interface and last but not least the documentation. See the MMCF module in www.mmbase.org/jira to view the complete issue list. Please contact the projectteam in case of questions.</body>
		<title>MMCF-day January 25, 2008</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The MMCF projectteam is working hard to get ready for the 1.9 release. The release date is now planned at the beginning of May 2008.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53110" owner="default">
		<body>Today another day of programming took place at the MMBase Foundation in Hilversum.

Food and accomodation was sponsored by the Foundation. Developers from Dynasol, Toly and Finalist worked together on finishing the 1.9 release.

The project team estimates that another six of those &quot;gezellige&quot; MMCF days are needed to finish the project. This means that an 1.9 release by the end of April 2008 is very likely.

To get an idea of the improvement entailed in the Component Framework 

Version of the CMSc admin menu WITH MMCF:

&lt;ul class=&quot;shortcuts&quot;&gt;
  &lt;mm:functioncontainer&gt;
    &lt;mm:param name=&quot;id&quot;&gt;cmsc.adminmenu&lt;/mm:param&gt;
    &lt;mm:listfunction set=&quot;components&quot; name=&quot;blockClassification&quot;&gt;
      &lt;c:forEach var=&quot;block&quot; items=&quot;${_.blocks}&quot;&gt;
     
	&lt;mm:component debug=&quot;xml&quot; name=&quot;${block.component.name}&quot; block=&quot;${block}&quot;&gt;
	&lt;/mm:component&gt;
      &lt;/c:forEach&gt;
    &lt;/mm:listfunction&gt;
  &lt;/mm:functioncontainer&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

Version of the CMSc admin menu WITHOUT MMCF:
&lt;ul class=&quot;shortcuts&quot;&gt;

	&lt;li class=&quot;users&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;../usermanagement/userlist.jsp&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.users&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;properties&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;../WizardListAction.do?nodetype=properties&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.settings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;layouts&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;../WizardListAction.do?nodetype=layout&quot;  target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.layouts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;views&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;../WizardListAction.do?nodetype=view&quot;  target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt; &lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.views&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;stylesheets&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;../WizardListAction.do?nodetype=stylesheet&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.stylesheets&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;portletdefinitions&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;../WizardListAction.do?wizardname=singleportletdefinition&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.singleportletdefinitions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;portletdefinitions&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;../WizardListAction.do?wizardname=multiportletdefinition&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.multiportletdefinitions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;dumpdefaults&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;dumpdefaults.jsp&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.dumpdefaults&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;clear&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;resetsitecache.jsp&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.resetsitecache&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li class=&quot;admindashboard&quot;&gt;
		!&lt;a href=&quot;../admindashboard&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;admin.admindashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;cmsc:hasfeature name=&quot;luceusmodule&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;luceus&quot;&gt;
       &lt;a href=&quot;../luceus/fullindex.jsp&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;modules.fullindex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/cmsc:hasfeature&gt;
    &lt;cmsc:hasfeature name=&quot;spidermodule&quot;&gt;
       &lt;li class=&quot;luceus&quot;&gt;
	  &lt;a href=&quot;../nijmegen/spiders.jsp&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;Nijmegen indexering GNS etc.&lt;/a&gt;
       &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/cmsc:hasfeature&gt;
    &lt;mm:haspage page=&quot;/editors/publish-remote&quot;&gt;
       &lt;li class=&quot;advancedpublish&quot;&gt;
	  &lt;c:url var=&quot;publishUrl&quot; value=&quot;/editors/publish-remote/index.jsp&quot;/&gt;
	  &lt;a href=&quot;${publishUrl}&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;modules.publish&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
       &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/mm:haspage&gt;
    &lt;mm:haspage page=&quot;/editors/workflow&quot;&gt;
       &lt;li class=&quot;workflow&quot;&gt;
	  &lt;c:url var=&quot;workflowUrl&quot; value=&quot;/editors/workflow/admin/WorkflowAdminAction.do&quot;/&gt;
	  &lt;a href=&quot;${workflowUrl}&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;modules.workflow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
       &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/mm:haspage&gt;
    &lt;mm:haspage page=&quot;/editors/knownvisitor-ntlm&quot;&gt;
       &lt;li class=&quot;visitor&quot;&gt;
	  &lt;c:url var=&quot;visitorNtlmUrl&quot; value=&quot;/editors/knownvisitor-ntlm/index.jsp&quot;/&gt;
	  &lt;a href=&quot;${visitorNtlmUrl}&quot; target=&quot;rightpane&quot;&gt;&lt;fmt:message key=&quot;modules.knowvisitor-html&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
       &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/mm:haspage&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;
</body>
		<title>The last six MMCF-days ;)</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The MMCF projectteam is working hard on finishing the MMBase Component Framework ...</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53195" owner="default">
		<body>Today the following code changes marked the moment of the 1.9 beta release.

public static boolean isRelease() {
-        return false;
+        return true;
 };

public static String getReleaseStatus() {
-        return &quot;&quot;;
+        return &quot;beta&quot;;
};


The 1.9 adds functionality for component based development to MMBase. Components that adhere to the component framework standard can be used across different MMBase applications. The release contains new admin pages, which actually are a cool example on how to use the component framework and its features like multi-language support. Especially the caches and applications pages in the 1.9 have been extended a lot by the use of the new framework. From the mmexaples the MyNews applications has been migrated.

You are invited to test the 1.9 beta release. If you run into issues which you can fix yourself you can create an issue in Jira and attach your fix to it. We did not find time to go through all the examples, so the install page and the examples can be regarded as known issues. For questions please use the developers mailing list or the irc channel. If you have run through your test please report your findings on the developers mailing list as well, including operating system, java version and database you used.

We would like to thank the MMCF project team for all hard work on this release. Special thanks go to the core members of the MMCF project: Michiel Meeuwissen, André van Toly and Nico Klasens.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.9 beta release is now available</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Today a completely new MMBase release was made ready to be tested.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53229" owner="default">
		<body>This release candidate has been upped for your testing purposes. It fixes numerous bugs and includes about a dozen new features like a broadened search in the EditWizards list pages, support for Java enumerations, sortable tables in my_editors etc. For a complete overview of all fixes and features, please refer to the release notes.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8.6 release candidate</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Besides the MMBase 1.9 beta release we are very proud of, the development team also created a release candidate of MMBase 1.8.6.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53361" owner="default">
		<body>New features include: varStatus attribute on list-tags like in JSTL, support for Java enums,  my_editors remember the sort direction of nodetypes on the index page, switch the small and wide columns in my_editors, added 'toweek' in Dateparse (useful in mm:time tag),  you can get properties from cloud, nodemanager, module, and more ways to search in the list.jsp in the EditWizards among others. 
And over  60 small bugs were fixed. You will find them all in the releasenotes.

</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.8.6 released</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Again more new features en bugfixes. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53479" owner="default">
		<body>The elegance of using a MMBase component can be best illustrated by this example:

  &lt;mm:link page=&quot;magazine&quot;&gt;
    &lt;mm:frameworkparam name=&quot;component&quot;&gt;mynews&lt;/mm:frameworkparam&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;${_}&quot;&gt;${_}&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/mm:link&gt;

This will typically generate a link to the MyNews application, or rather its component, depending on the location of your webapp: http://www.localhost:8080/example-1.9.0/magazine. The new tag &lt;mm:frameworkparam /&gt; is responsible for the generation of a userfriendly link, provided that the component is accompanied by an UrlConverter generating user- and searchengine friendly links.

The component itself, and with that the omni present MyNews application, can be included in your webpage with the following example:

  &lt;mm:component name=&quot;mynews&quot; /&gt;

Which will show the introduction of the MyNews magazine followed by a list of the well known articles. More information, for example about how to build your own components, can be found in the documentation.</body>
		<title>MMCF released with MMBase 1.9.0</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>This release includes the long awaited MMBase Component Framework designed to make sharing applications and other functionality build upon MMBase easier.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53762" owner="default">
		<body>A subversion repository to test with can be found at: 

https://scm.mmbase.org/

IOW you can do a full check out like so:

svn co https://scm.mmbase.org/mmbase/trunk

Note that this is based on the contents of CVS of about a month ago. When everybody is content, we will redo it with a fresh copy. For the moment this is just to explore how it would work. As yet, the https certificate is not signed, so please accept the exception. 

The migration itself will take place on the 1st of May. Versioning will be down fow a few hours, and it's convenient if all pending changes are checked in before that, because during and after the conversion CVS will be offline, and afterwards we'll have to use subversion.
Stay tuned to the users and developers mailing lists for the lastest information.</body>
		<title>MMBase is migrating to SVN</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>We are planning to migrate the MMBase CVS repository to Subversion. We tested how that would go, and it went well. The migration is planned for the 1st of May.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53826" owner="default">
		<body>Not only did MMBase move from CVS to Subversion and did our build system change from Ant, to Maven 1.1 to Maven 2, the release team even found some time to release a new minor version of MMBase: 1.9.1. 

Please refer to the release notes for a complete overview.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.9.1 released</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The first bug fix release of 1.9 with several improvements and new features.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="53952" owner="default">
		<body>Michiel developed a prototype, which is a bit similar to the contributed code of Kennisnet.

The prototype supports REST
- configuration via xml
- webservices can be created by implementing:
a. an interface
b. a bean
c. an MMBase function
d. an MMBase component 'block' which produces XML (so it can be done in JSP)

The servlet supports different return-types via extension, and parameters are validated via mmbase datatypes.
Authentication is carried out via  mmbase 'actions' (a concept that is new sinceMMBase-1.9).

You find this back in:
https://scm.mmbase.org/speeltuin/mihxil/webservice/mmbase/src/main/config/webservices.xml

There is an 'example webapp'. which can be runned via jetty:run in a checkout of
https://scm.mmbase.org/speeltuin/mihxil/webservice/example-webapp

Decisions:
-develop a document-type for article (and its related assets and metadata)
-specification of services module that handles article, this module should be configurable to also support other document types (XML / Java)

To do:
- send Jo examples of articles as they are used in CMSc, Copacabana, Patmos (all)
- proposal document type (Jo, deadline Sept 16)
- review prototype (Nico)
- work on proposal on how to implement services module (Nico, Johannes, Michiel)

Next meeting: Thursday October 1, 2009, 18:00h</body>
		<title>Minutes MMBase developers meeting September 10, 2009</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro></intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54007" owner="default">
		<body>Locatie: Stichting Kennisnet, Paletsingel 32, Zoetermeer
In de ochtend vindt de 11e CMSc-gebruikersdag plaats. De agenda hiervoor is rondgestuurd.

13.15-16.00 uur MMEvent 2009

13.25-13.30 Welkomstwoord door vertegenwoordiger Kennisnet

13.35-14.00 Maarten Brinkerink (beeld en Geluid) en Andre van Toly (www.toly.nl) over de ontwikkeling die ze voor Beeld en Geluid hebben gedaan. Open Beelden is een open mediaplatform dat toegang biedt tot audiovisuele collecties die eenvoudig hergebruikt kunnen worden. Een voorbeeld van daarvan is het ‘remixen’ van archiefmateriaal in nieuw werk. Deze nieuwe werken kunnen gebruikers vervolgens ook weer aan het platform toevoegen. Open Beelden biedt daarnaast een API, wat het gemakkelijk maakt om mashups te ontwikkelen.zie http://www.openbeelden.nl
- MMBase Streams applicatie die m.b.v. FFmpeg en FFmpeg2Theora streams (audio en video) ter plekke converteerd naar verschillende Open Source formaten, waaronder Ogg maar ook h.264 mpeg. Dat gebeurt ongeveer op dezelfde manier als MMBase nu afbeeldingen converteerd met ImageMagick.
- Uitbreidingen op de huidige Media applicatie om het bovenstaande te ondersteunen.
- Een geheel multitalige versie van de site waarin alle nodes op veldniveau vertaald kunnen worden.
- HTML5 video en audiotags om de streams af te spelen.

14.00-14.30 Lucas Vroemen (Innovatiemanager L1). De ontwikkelingen in de mediawereld gaan razendsnel, dat vraagt om open technologie die flexibel meegroeit met de steeds veranderende wensen en eisen. Spreker: Lucas Vroemen (innovatiemanager L1)

14.30-14.50 Hendrik Hangyi, projectmanager Proteon. Vergelijking tussen verschillende Open Source Content Management Systemen, in het bijzonder Hippo en CMSc.

14.50-15.10 Michiel Meeuwissen. Komende release(s) van MMBase en recente ontwikkelingen aan de core.

15.10-15.30: Minne Oostra en Peter van Kampen (De Ontwikkelfabriek).  De site  www.aletta.nu is een succesvol voorbeeld van integratie tussen CMSc en Solr (Apache Lucene project). Zoeken in grote hoeveelheden geclassificeerde data. Hoe werkt dat.

15.30-15.45 Johannes Verelst (Evangelische Omroep) Naar een uniforme manier van MMBase Webservices.

15.45-16.00 Jo Lahaye (Stichting MMBase/CMSc). Waarom bedenkt elke organisatie steeds weer opnieuw de eigenschappen van een nieuwsbericht of agenda-item? Kan dat anders? 

16.00: Borrel. Kennisnet en de Stichting MMBase/CMSc bieden de aanwezigen graag een hapje en een drankje aan.
</body>
		<title>Annual CMSc and MMEvent: 15 december (Dutch)</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Het jaarlijkse CMSc/MMEvent wordt in 2009 gehouden bij Kennisnet in Zoetermeer. </intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54056" owner="default">
		<body>We hope to release the next bugfix and new feature rich version of MMBase 1.9 soon. </body>
		<title>MMBase 1.9.2 release candidate</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>For all your testing pleasures the release team has made a MMBase 1.9.2-rc2 available.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54152" owner="default">
		<body>This release includes 50 bugfixes and some improvements. 

Streams accompanies the already existing Media application in use by several broadcastings organisations. Streams encodes video and audio to other formats with the help of FFmpeg. Streams is developed for Open Images ('Open Beelden' in Dutch), an initiative of the Netherlands Institute for Sound and Vision (Nederlands Instutuut voor Beeld en Geluid) in collaboration with the Knowledgeland (Nederland Kennisland). Open Images is an open media platform that offers online access to audiovisual archive material to stimulate creative reuse. Footage from audiovisual collections can be downloaded and remixed into new works. Users of Open Images also have the opportunity to add their own material to the platform and thus expand the collection.

Other improvements include among others the ability to change the nodemanager (nodetype) of a node, numerous unit tests, improvements on the Search and Relate application, and the introduction of org.mmbase.bridge.mock a mock bridge to be used for example for testing.

Besides 1.9.2 the release team released 1.8.7, a bugfix release of the 1.8 branch.</body>
		<title>MMBase 1.9.2 released (and 1.8.7)</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The latest release of MMBase with a ton of new features and bugfixes. One of the most notable new features is the new Streams application that encodes uploaded video and audio to other formats. Besides 1.9.2 a bugfix release of the 1.8 branch was released.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54277" owner="default">
		<body>The release team recently released this one with a total of 39 bug fixes and new features.</body>
		<title>Release of MMBase 1.9.3</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>A bugfix release of the stable MMBase 1.9 branch.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54463" owner="default">
		<body>MMBase-1.9.4 is a bugfix release, containing a few small new features. See the release notes for more details about the 25 issues new, fixed or improved.</body>
		<title>Release of 1.9.4</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>It is already two weeks ago, but we released MMBase-1.9.4. It is a bugfix release, containing a few small new features.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54470" owner="default">
		<body>The new server ('alfred') will replace the old ones ('james' and 'jeeves'), and is sponsored by the MMBase foundation. It will be administrated by Andre and Michiel. Alfred seems to be the name of some butler too; Andre came up with it. 

It will cause a down time of several hours for the website and jira. Subversion may be down for longer, and possibly will only work again after the weekend.</body>
		<title>New MMBase-server</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>Tomorrow a new server will be installed for MMBase.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54508" owner="default">
		<body>MMBase.org is on a new server (a debian 5.0 installation). Plus our site is now finally running MMBase 1.9.</body>
		<title>MMBase server is successfully upgraded!</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>If your are reading this your doing so are from our new piece of hardware. But of course Friday the 13th could be a bit risky date when you believe in such things...</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54529" owner="default">
		<body>In the past we had something like five different lists. Separate lists for not only developers and users, but also for CMS Container, announce etc. These have been brought together in just one list: mmbase-discuss at Google Groups.

If you had a subscription to one of these lists, you will have to newly subscribe again. Google Groups has no option to import existing subscriptions, but some of you have had an invitation to which you can easily reply. 
</body>
		<title>Mailing lists moved</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>We stopped maintaining our own mailing lists and moved them to Google Groups. Visit http://groups.google.com/group/mmbase-discuss/subscribe to subscribe again.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="54683" owner="default">
		<body>MMBase-1.9.5 is a bugfix release, containing a some new features like for example added new mime types, fixes in upload and the streams application. See the release notes for more details about issues new, fixed or improved.</body>
		<title>Release of 1.9.5</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>We have recently release a new update of MMBase: version 1.9.5 with a few bugfixes and new features.</intro>
	</node>

	<node number="55378" owner="default">
		<body>A rather long awaited bug fix release with over 40 issues fixed, improved or newly featured. Check the release notes for a complete overview.</body>
		<title>Release of 1.9.6</title>
		<subtitle></subtitle>
		<intro>The release team just released a new version of MMBase, version 1.9.6.</intro>
	</node>

</news>
